<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An after-reckoning with Mr Saltmarsh: or, An appeal to the impartiall and consciencious reader, and lover of truth and sincerity, against his last paper, called An end of one controversy, or an answer or letter to M. Leys large last book. Written by L.M. a student in divinity.</title>
            <author>Ley, John, 1583-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88098</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1870</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E339_20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200863</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861489</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861489</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113626</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88098)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113626)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 55:E339[20])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An after-reckoning with Mr Saltmarsh: or, An appeal to the impartiall and consciencious reader, and lover of truth and sincerity, against his last paper, called An end of one controversy, or an answer or letter to M. Leys large last book. Written by L.M. a student in divinity.</title>
                  <author>Ley, John, 1583-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 56, 53-59, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Christopher Meredith, at the signe of the Crane in Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>L.M. = John Ley.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Saltmarsh, John.  An end of one controversie (Wing S479).</note>
                  <note>"M. Leys large last book" = "Light for smoke".</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 5".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Saltmarsh, John, d. 1647. --  End of one controversie --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ley, John, 1583-1662. --  Light for smoke --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113626:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113626:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN AFTER-RECKONING WITH M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>SALTMARSH:</hi> OR, An appeal to the impartiall and conſciencious Reader, and Lover of Truth and Sincerity, AGAINST His laſt paper, called <hi>An end of one controverſy,</hi> or an Anſwer or Letter to M. <hi>Leys</hi> large laſt Book.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>L. M.</hi> a Student in Divinity.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 11.19.</hi>
               </bibl> The lip of truth ſhall be eſtabliſhed for ever, but a lying tongue is but for a moment.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſ. 12.11.</hi>
               </bibl> The words of the wiſe are as goa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, and as nails faſtened by the maſters of Aſſemblies.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Act 9.30.</hi>
               </bibl> —It ſhall be determined in a lawfull Aſsembly.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Hieron. Apolog. <hi>adverſ.</hi> Iovin. <hi>Tom. 2 p. 109.</hi>
               </bibl> Sciolitantum ad detra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>endum, qui in coſe doctos oſtent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re velint, ſi omnium dicta lacerent.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Chriſtopher Meredith,</hi> at the Signe of the Crane in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113626:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113626:2"/>
            <head>To the indifferent Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader, this <hi>After-reckoning</hi> with M. <hi>Saltm,</hi> was prepared for the preſse the next week after he had ſent forth his paper, called, <hi>The end of one Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy,</hi> which was time enough for anſwer to ſuch a ſmall trifle as that was, begun and ended within the compaſſe of a ſheet and an half; but the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour not importuning for the expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion uſed in M. <hi>Saltm.</hi> his cauſe, for which two preſſes have ſometimes been employed to give haſty diſpatch to a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle pamphlet; but leaving them to their own pace, and pawſes, (who ſometimes make a broad blank margin of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, as well as a leaf of laborious im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion)
<pb facs="tcp:113626:3"/>it hath been lingring in the preſſe untill this preſent. Yet that delay will be recompenſed in part by an addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall of ſatisfaction in a point of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy of ſome moment, more then the juſt proportion of a <hi>Reply</hi> to ſuch a writer, and ſuch matter did neceſſarily require. Whereby that thou mayeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive direction without errour, be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to take notice of theſe miſpriſions and corrections of the Printer.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata ſic corrigenda.</head>
            <p>PAge 1. l. 23. for <hi>wherein</hi> read <hi>In the Anſwer.</hi> p. 3. l. 5. for <hi>prevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate</hi> r <hi>prevaricating.</hi> p. 5. l. 3 after <hi>Mordecai</hi> r. <hi>alone,</hi> and l. 4. after <hi>deſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> r. <hi>all.</hi> p. 19. adde to M. <hi>Saltm</hi> his Text cited out of the 7. page of his paper, this, <hi>Are we to be ever conſulting with fleſh and blood? did the Diſciples and brethren when they ſpake the Word of God, tugge firſt among ſo, many Schoolmen? So many Fathers? So many moderne Divines? So many Commentators? So many old Poets, as you doe?</hi> p. 33. l. 29 dele <hi>and who.</hi> p. 46 l. 11. for <hi>Thirdly</hi> r. <hi>Secondly.</hi> p. 40. l. 25. for <hi>own</hi> r. <hi>one.</hi> p. 51. l. 11. make a parentheſis of 3. lines and a peece, from the word <hi>which</hi> to the word <hi>authors,</hi> incluſively for both ends of it. p. 53. l. 5. before the end blot out the figure [1] p. 54. l. 15. for <hi>imployed</hi> r. <hi>implyed.</hi> p. 55. marg. lit. K. for <hi>quia</hi> r <hi>quin.</hi> p. 56. l. ult. for <hi>ſwarivng</hi> r. <hi>ſwarving. In</hi> M. <hi>L.</hi> his <hi>Light for ſmoke</hi> p. 16. l. 5. for <hi>Presbyteriall</hi> r. <hi>Prelaticall.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:113626:3"/>
            <head>The Contents of this After-reckoning.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y little and cheap pamphlets the people de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded, and better books, if bigger and deaerer, unjuſtly prejudiced. <hi>p. 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> M. <hi>Saltm.</hi> makes his return with leſſe conſcience then the unjuſt ſteward, <hi>Luk. 16.6. p. 2.</hi> and muchwhat like a bankrupt. <hi>p. 7.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> A miniſtry received from the hands of Proteſtant Biſhops, neither Antichristian, nor to be renounced. <hi>p. 3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> M. <hi>Saltm.</hi> his ſcoffing miſapplication of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture in the title page of his Paper anſwered, and cenſured. <hi>p. 4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> Vnworthy perſons cryed up in a time of ſchiſme, who in times of peace were of no good note, nor of good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt. <hi>p. 5.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> It is no diſparagement to truth to be frequently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, nor any point of popery to write volumes and Tomes, as M. <hi>S.</hi> pretendeth. <hi>p. 5, 6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> His objection of reference to others anſwered. <hi>p. 7, 8, 9,</hi> and <hi>p. 21.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> His vain conceipt that an advice for his better em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment was out of fear of the potency of his pen, diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and confuted. p. 10, 11. <hi>ſee the like. p. 13, 14.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> M. <hi>Saltm.</hi> his abſurd compariſon of prelacy and presbytery in point of tyranny. <hi>p. 11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> Of a twoſold restitution, in fact, or in affection. <hi>p. 12.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:113626:4"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>11.</hi> Of formes of art and Logick, the ſchool of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and of <hi>Tyrannus,</hi> and of diſcoveries of Chriſt by reaſon. <hi>p. 14, 15, 16,</hi> And of humane learning. <hi>p. 19, 22.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12.</hi> M. <hi>Salm.</hi> not ſlandered by M. <hi>L.</hi> with any erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous opinion. <hi>p. 16, 17, 18.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13.</hi> His poor ſhift to excuſe his unfaithfull dealing with M. <hi>Sam. Bolton. p. 17, 18.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14.</hi> Exceſſe in diſpatch and deliberation compared, and miſapplyed by M. <hi>S. p. 19.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15.</hi> M. <hi>Saltm.</hi> his ſelf-confidence, and rare dexteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in contracting and contradicting. <hi>p. 21.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16.</hi> Of Tithes and their Tenure. <hi>p. 23.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17.</hi> M. <hi>S.</hi> his frivolous exceptions and anſwers. <hi>p. 24, 25.</hi> A clear vindication of M. <hi>L.</hi> from vain oſtentation, ſuggeſted by M. <hi>S.</hi> out of <hi>C. D.</hi> his defence of M. <hi>Ley.</hi> a <hi>p. 16.</hi> ad <hi>33.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18.</hi> M. <hi>Saltm.</hi> in his collections and concealments ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unſincere and unfaithfull. <hi>p. 33, 34.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>19.</hi> M. <hi>Saltm.</hi> his vain pretence of diſcovery of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours miſtaken for truths by M <hi>L. p. 35, 36.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>20.</hi> His <hi>Concluſion</hi> compounded of calumny, arrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and hypocriſie. a <hi>p. 36.</hi> ad <hi>p. 40.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>21.</hi> A <hi>Review</hi> of the repetition of <hi>Salmaſius</hi> his Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, <hi>1.</hi> Touching Baptiſme. <hi>p. 41.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>22.</hi> M. <hi>S.</hi> his immodest inſiſting in the ſaying of <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſius,</hi> after a full anſwer unto it.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>23.</hi> Of the form of Baptiſme, preparative and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, firſt of the preparative. <hi>p. 42, 43.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>24.</hi> Five Queries of the form of Baptiſme,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Whether there be any form of words for the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Baptiſme at all, whether <hi>John</hi> uſed any form? <hi>p. 45.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:113626:4"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> Whether we finde one certain and conſtant form of Baptiſme, either preſcribed or obſerved in Scripture, and what difference of forms may be collected out of it? <hi>p. 45, 46, 47, 48.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>25. The third Querie,</hi> Of the ſeverall forms of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſme which is the chief? <hi>p. 49.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>26.</hi> The chief is that which is grounded on, <hi>Mat. 28.19. viz.</hi> baptizing <hi>In the name of the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt. p. 49.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <label>For it,</label>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> Scripture. <hi>p. 49, 50.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> Reaſon. <hi>p. 50.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> Practicall example. <hi>p. 50.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>4.</hi> The teſtimony of ancient Fathers. <hi>p. 51.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>5.</hi> The teſtimony of Schoolmen. <hi>p. 51.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>6.</hi> The teſtimony of the reformed Churches. <hi>p. 52.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>27.</hi> Of baptizing by trine immerſion, or thrice dipping, as a practicall profeſsion of Baptiſme, <hi>In the name of the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt. p. 52, 53.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>28. The fourth Querie,</hi> Whether any form of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſme be ſo neceſſary, that it is not lawfull to vary from it? <hi>p. 53.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>29.</hi> The Apoſtles thought to baptize ſometimes <hi>In the Name of the Trinity. p. 54.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>30.</hi> Of baptizing in termes equivalent to <hi>In the Name of the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt. p. 54.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>31.</hi> Not lawfull now to alter the form of Baptiſme <hi>In the Name of the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt. p. 55.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>32. The fifth Querie,</hi> If there be any variation from the form, in <hi>Mat. 28.19.</hi> what may be admitted without the violation of the Sacrament, what not? <hi>p. 55.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:113626:5"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>33.</hi> Of Baptizing in the firſt perſon, <hi>I Baptize,</hi> or in the third <hi>perſon, as the Greeks doe, Let this ſervant of Chriſt be Baptized. p. 55.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>34.</hi> Of putting <hi>ſprinkle,</hi> or <hi>waſh,</hi> for <hi>Baptize,</hi> and of baptizing, <hi>In the name,</hi> or <hi>Into the name. p. 56.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>35.</hi> Expreſsmention of the three perſons in the Trinity how neceſsary? <hi>p. 56.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>36.</hi> Of a popiſh Prieſt baptizing in falſe Latine, <hi>In nomine Patria, Filia, &amp; Spiritua Sancta. p. 56.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>37.</hi> Of hereticall forms of Baptiſme by <hi>Marcus</hi> the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike, by <hi>Arians, Eunomians,</hi> and <hi>Photinians. p. 57.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>38.</hi> Of the <hi>Montaniſts</hi> adding the Name of <hi>Montanus</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> to the perſons of the Trinity in Baptiſme. <hi>p. 58.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>39.</hi> Of Popiſh Baptiſme with addition of the Virgin <hi>Maries</hi> name to the Trinity in Baptiſme. <hi>p. 58.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>40.</hi> Of Baptizing <hi>In the name of God and the true croſſe</hi> excuſed by <hi>Bernard. p. 58.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>41.</hi> What is to be done when there is doubt of the form of Baptiſme? <hi>p. 59.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>42.</hi> Of M. <hi>Saltm</hi> his exception againſt baptizing <hi>In the Name of the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt. p. 59, 60.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>43.</hi> His miſapplication of <hi>Salmaſius</hi> his teſtimony for patronage of his opinion. <hi>p. 60, 61.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>44.</hi> An <hi>Animadverſion</hi> upon the unſavoury Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet called <hi>A perfume,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p. 61, 62.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ja. Cranford.</signed>
               <date>May <hi>28. 1646.</hi>
               </date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113626:5"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Praeloquium.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Leys</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>S.</hi> his Books were both of a price, and ordinary Readers would not he ſuch truants at their Books, as to be beſt pleaſed with the ſhorteſt leſſon, there might now (as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Salt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marſh</hi> ſtiles his laſt Pamphlet) be an <hi>end of one controverſie,</hi> (this one betwixt M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Ley</hi> and him,) and he ſhould now have (that which he often ſtriveth for) as well the laſt word as the firſt, in quarrels of this kinde: But ſince M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Leys</hi> Book is twelve times as dear as his, and more then twelve times as bigg, it cannot be expected that the number of buyers, or Readers of both their writings will be equall, and ſo both truth and innocence may ſuffer under a common pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, if this laſt Pamphlet of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>S.</hi> ſhould ſeal up the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence betwixt them to perpetuall ſilence.</p>
               <p>I ſhall therefore briefly and faithfully ſet before the Reader ſome particulars or importance, whereby he may the better judge which of theſe two Antagoniſts carrieth his cauſe with cleareſt evidence of truth and ſincerity, and the ſumme of what I ſhall ſay ſhall be reduced to theſe two heads.</p>
               <p n="1">1. An Apologeticall anſwer to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>S.</hi> his objections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>L.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. A freſh charge of objections againſt M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Saltmarſh.</hi> Wherein I ſhall diſtinctly conſider in M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>S.</hi> his paper,
<list>
                     <item>1. The Title page.</item>
                     <item>2. His Letter.</item>
                     <item>3. His Summary accompt of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                        <hi>Leys</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. Epiſtle.</item>
                           <item>2. Treatiſe.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. His Anſwer to it.</item>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:113626:6"/>
                     <item>5. His reinforcing of <hi>Salmaſius</hi> his Teſtimony.</item>
                     <item>6. His Deſcant on <hi>C. D.</hi> his Defence of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> L. againſt the Newſmonger.</item>
                     <item>7. His ſelf-commending Concluſion.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>1.</hi> For his Title page.</p>
               <p>J. S.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An end of one Controverſie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The end of one Controverſie, as you uſe the matter, may be the beginning of another. If you had meant it ſhould have been an end of the Controverſie, you would not have taken leave of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Ley,</hi> with ſuch an abuſe of his Book, and reproach of his perſon, as could not be paſſed by with ſilence of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf or his friends; unleſſe the moſt did agree with the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt in the cenſure of the ſleightneſſe and inſufficiency of your Anſwer, as unworthy to receive any reply, but ſuch a one as is unſeemly for him to make.</p>
               <p>Title.</p>
               <p>J. S.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Being an Anſwer or Letter to M</hi> Leys <hi>Large laſt Book.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So ſhort an anſwer to ſo large a Book? ſure you never meant to make any Reader (that could judge as well as read) beleeve that your ſheet and half could be a ſatisfactory An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Leys</hi> Book, which you ſumme up to 17 ſheets of paper, (beſides the Treatiſe of <hi>C. D.</hi>) unleſſe your haſty return make up a great part of the ſumme, as in the accompt of the or juſt ſteward, fifty meaſures of oyl, quickly written down, ſtood for 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. as <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.6.</p>
               <p>Title.</p>
               <p>J. S.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In which the ſumme of his laſt Book, which relates to the moſt materiall paſſages in it, are gathered up and replyed to.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſumme is ſoon taken, as of the number of ſheets, and you might do moſt of that without ſo much as reading of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113626:6"/>Book; for M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Ley</hi> ſummed up each ſection into ſhort con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, preſently after the Epiſtle Dedicatory; but for your Reply unto it, it is ſo poor, impertinent and unſatisfactory, that you had done your ſelf more favour if you had been alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſilent, then in acting the part of ſuch a prevaricate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicant as you have done.</p>
               <p>Title.</p>
               <p>J. S.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By</hi> John Saltmarſh: <hi>not revolted (as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
                  </hi> Ley <hi>ſaith) from a paſtorall calling, but departed from the Antichriſtian Miniſtery by Biſhops and now Preacher of the Goſpel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You have given over your publike Miniſtery at <hi>Braſteed,</hi> and if you have forſaken as Antichriſtian, that is more then M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Ley</hi> charged you with, in the Title page of his Book; whence it may be probably conjectured, that you either have, or will renounce your Baptiſme, ſince it was adminiſtred by one ordained by a Biſhop, and ſo in your dialect an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian Miniſter; and upon this ground many, who know not how to diſtinguiſh of Miniſteriall Acts, will haply be induced to ſuſpect their parents marriage by ſuch a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to be Antichriſtian: and that will call in queſtion the legitimacy of the children: but none of theſe conſequences can trouble thoſe, who hold, as the Lords and Commons in their Ordinance for Ordination of Miniſters have declared, viz. <hi>That although the Title of Biſhop hath been by corrupt cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom appropriated to one, and that unto him aſcribed, and by him aſſumed (as in other things, ſo in the matter of</hi> Ordination) <hi>which was not meet; Ordination notwithſtanding being performed by him, a</hi> Presbyter, <hi>joyned with other</hi> Presbyters, <hi>We hold for ſubſtance to be valid, and not to be diſclaimed by any that have received it. And that</hi> Presbyters <hi>ſo ordained, being lawfully thereunto appointed and authorized, may ordain other</hi> Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2.</hi> The places of Scripture miſapplied.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:113626:7"/>
               <p>J. S.</p>
               <p>Iſa. 5.20. <hi>We be to them that put darkneſſe for light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Scripture in the ſenſe of it, maketh as much for M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Ley</hi> as for you; and in the letter more; for he put not dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for light, but <hi>light for ſmoke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>J. S.</p>
               <p>Acts 19.32. <hi>Some therefore cried one thing and ſome another, for the Aſſembly was confuſed, and the more part knew not where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were come together.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Verſ. 41. <hi>And when he had thus spoken he diſmiſſed the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Ley</hi> is ſtiled one of the Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> you take occaſion to abuſe the Aſſembly; and that you may abuſe them, you abuſe the Scripture, by miſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the Text to them, which was ſpoken of a tumultuary meeting of <hi>Demetrius</hi> with his company, and the Idolatrous worſhippers of <hi>Diana,</hi> confuſedly come together they knew not why: And to make your meaning the more apparent, you write <hi>Aſſembly</hi> in greater letters then the reſt. With what diſcretion can you fall upon them, who did not meddle with you at all, though you did what you could to provoke them? with what conſcience can you compare a learned, religious and Reverend Aſſembly of Divines (who were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led together by the Parliament, for cauſes known, not only to themſelves, but all the Kingdom over, who neither meet nor part without religious addreſſes to the throne of grace) to ſuch a ſuperſtitious, ignorant and mutinous multitude?</p>
               <p>But you meant not only to diſgrace them, but to threaten <hi>them with diſmiſſion alſo,</hi> or at leaſt you intimate your minde to have it ſo, and all of your way have ſuch ill will unto it, that your firſt deſires were to prevent it, your next to diſturbe it, and delay the proceedings of it, and now out of the ſame diſaffection to it you deſire to diſſolve it. But why you, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>S.</hi> ſhould bring in the Aſſembly in ſuch a malignant manner, is a matter much noted by ſome, and though they know not the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113626:7"/>reaſon, they conjecture at theſe two cauſes thereof; the one is, the pride of your ſpirit, like that of <hi>Haman,</hi> who thought ſcorn to lay hands upon <hi>Mordecai,</hi> and therefore ſought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the <hi>Jews, Eſther</hi> 3.6. though thoſe that know M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Ley</hi> and you, ſay, there is <hi>impar congreſſus</hi> betwixt you, by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage on his ſide, though <hi>Haman</hi> like you had not ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Aſſembly; yet as if he were not good enough alone to be your match, you fetch that venerable Synod within the verge of your reproof; ſuch a giant you are now grown to be, by being leader of a ſchiſme, who had been but a pygmie ſtill, if you had continued among the Presbyterians; juſt as <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> obſerved of <hi>Primianus</hi> and <hi>Maximinianus,</hi> that were jolly fellows in a faction, elſe, ſaid he, <hi>Primianus</hi> might have been <hi>Poſtremianus,</hi> and <hi>Maximianus, Minimianus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The other conjecture is this, you have honoured the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly too much, for you almoſt adored them, and made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications of Scripture to them, which had a ſtrong ſavour of Idolatry and flattery, little below the height of blaſphemy, and now you, declining that extreme, ſtay not your ſelf untill,<note n="*" place="margin">Dam vitant ſtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i vitia is contraria cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> 
                  <hi>Wiſeman</hi> like, you arrive at the contrary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2.</hi> The ſecond particular is your Letter, <hi>wherein you ſay,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>J. S. p. 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I thinke not the truth I defended ſo weak as to need a new Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe to bear it up; I ſee it is otherwiſe with you, who dare not let your former Books stand by themſelves, without another to ſupport them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Ley</hi> had made none anſwer at all, you would have taken his ſilence for conſent; his ſilence after ſuch a charge as you laid upon him, for a confeſſion of guilt, and now he hath anſwered you, make that an argument of a weak cauſe that adjective-like needs a ſubſtantive ſupport of another book, when that was not the weakneſſe of the former book, but your waywardneſſe againſt it, whereby you hoped to wrangle your ſelf into ſome reputation, by out wording your adverſary, as it were all one to be able to anſwer, and unable
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113626:8"/>to hold ones peace; and whereas you ſay, that you call the <hi>truth needs no new Treatiſe,</hi> what, I pray you, call you this you have laſt written? You call your former Book <hi>an Anſwer,</hi> ſo do you this; you call this <hi>a Letter,</hi> ſo do you not that; yet you make M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>L.</hi> his <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> whereof the one conteineth 3 leaves, the other 9, a competent Treatiſe of themſelves; and yet of your ſheet and half you ſay, that he that writes any thing of truth, more properly writes much, rather then he that writes againſt it, though in more paper: That's your Aphoriſme framed and applied in favour to your ſelf, but you muſt not be your own judge.</p>
               <p>The Letter.</p>
               <p>J. S. p. 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is indeed the way of the Popiſh ſchools, to fill the world with volumes and Tomes, and rather to aſtoniſh then convince.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And is it not the way of the Proteſtant ſchools, to make up the fullneſſe of that world with volumes and Tomes? have not <hi>Luther, Zuinglius, Calvin, Beza, Martyr, Bucer, Gualter, Zanchius, Chamier</hi> and others, made many and great books? will you make that their fault which was their vertue; their blame, which is their glory and the Churches gain?</p>
               <p>Letter.</p>
               <p>J. S. p. 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How hath truth been carried out of ſight from the Reader in the labyrinth of Replyes and Rejoynders, your ſelfe gives us an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment in this book; for how are you puzled to let the Reader know what was yours, and what was mine after that, and what is yours again?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>M. <hi>Ley</hi> was not puzled, but that the Reader might not be puzled, nor miſtaken by your imperfect, unfaithfull and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Anſwers, he brought as much both of his Text and yours alſo, as might ſufficiently clear the truth to his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113626:8"/>
               <p>Letter.</p>
               <p>J. S. p. 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I hope I ſhall write you as much, if not more, in one ſheet and half, as you have wrote me in ſeventeen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Belike you have ſome ſuch art of couching much matter in a little room, as he that<note n="*" place="margin">Plin. <hi>nat. biſt.</hi> l. 7. c. 21. p 35.</note> compriſed <hi>Homers Iliads</hi> in a nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhell; or you return the paiment in gold which you received but in ſilver, or but in farthing tokens; that as much in value, this more in weight and more troubleſome, becauſe longer in telling; but, Sir, they that have read M. <hi>Leys</hi> book, and your ſheet and half, ſay, your return unto him is after the manner of poor bankrupts, or below that, not paying of the debt you ow him, ſo much as two ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llings in the pound; and they take your compariſon and prelation of your ſelf in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, to be but a very vain vaunting of your ſelf, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayeth your want both of truth and modeſty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The third Particular is,</hi> Your ſummary accompt of M. <hi>Leys</hi> Book. And first of the Epiſtles, <hi>p. 4.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>J. S.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Your Epiſtles, which are a competent Treatiſe of themſelves, and the very ciſterne of your reaſoning, from which you fill all the other pages of your Book; the parts of my Treatiſe, with your Anſwer, or rather much of your former Reply, which in things of moſt weight is no refutation, but a reference to other Divines who have writ of the ſame ſubject.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You preſume the moſt of thoſe who read your papers, are the feweſt of thoſe that read M. <hi>Leys</hi> book; but there are ſo many learned and judicious perſons, who have read them both, that there cannot but be many witneſſes of your foul and unfaithfull dealing with him, and with your Readers in this imputation.</p>
               <p>Sumons. <hi>p. 4.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>J. S.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It ſeems you have a common ſtock of learning among you,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113626:9"/>or an argumentative treaſury, to which you refer us with much eaſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How doth it ſeem that Presbyterians have a common ſtock of learning among them, or an argumentative treaſury? is it becauſe, when one man hath copiouſly and exactly diſcuſſed a point of weight, a reference is made unto him for further ſatisfaction then can be expected in a diſcourſe of ſo many particulars as you ſhuffle and jumble together in your darke and ſmoky Treatiſe? and is the book he cited any more his treaſury then yours, or any mans elſe that will buy it, and uſe it? Did you manage any matter of difference like a ſcholar, by ſtating of the Queſtion, propoſing of proofs by Scripture and reaſon, to which he hath not returned a punctuall An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer? Indeed you took upon you to put tasks upon him, which he did not undertake, and yet held your ſelf free to leave your own worke undone, and you give him cauſe<note n="*" place="margin">Light for Smoke. Sect. 4. p. 8. &amp; Sect. 5. p. 11. &amp; Sect. 16. p. 42.</note> divers times to complain of this partiality.</p>
               <p>Summe. <hi>p. 4.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>J. S.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But I cannot take this for good paiment, to be put over to another man, when you are bound to pay me your ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is there any either law, or conſcience, or reaſon, that he ſhould pay you any thing who owes you nothing? or any reaſon why you ſhould complain of non-payment, when M. <hi>Ley</hi> is far before hand with you, as any indifferent auditour betwixt him and you will give in the accompt? And yet if he ought you any thing, it is ſufficient if you be paid, whether it be by his hand or by another; and I hope before you and I part, to pay you ſomewhat in his ſtead, while he is imployed in matters of greater moment.</p>
               <p>Summe. <hi>p. 4.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>J. S.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I could turn you over thus to as able Divines as you do me, to M.</hi> Tho. Goodwin, <hi>M.</hi> Joh. Goodwin, <hi>M.</hi> Nye, <hi>M.</hi> Tomes, <hi>M.</hi> Prinne, <hi>M.</hi> Burroughs, <hi>M.</hi> White, <hi>M.</hi> Eaton, <hi>M.</hi> Den, <hi>M.</hi> Knolls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:113626:9"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>M. <hi>Ley</hi> turned you over to none for any argument you brought in the difference betwixt him and you; but when you would put upon him <hi>in tranſitu,</hi> the handling of a large Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, (wherein you had not engaged your ſelf by under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking the proof) he referred you to M. <hi>Rutherfords</hi> book. Now whereas you ſay you could turn him over to as able Divines as he doth you, <hi>viz.</hi> to M. <hi>Thomas Goodwin,</hi> M. <hi>John Goodwin,</hi> M. <hi>Nye,</hi> M. <hi>Tombes,</hi> M. <hi>Prinne,</hi> M. <hi>Burroughs,</hi> M. <hi>White,</hi> M. <hi>Eaton,</hi> M. <hi>Denne,</hi> M. <hi>Knolls,</hi> you make your compariſon very unequall; for, firſt, M. <hi>Rutherford</hi> for his great learning, and gravity, and ſeniority, may well be your Maſter; whereas you will not ſay the ſame of thoſe you have named with reſpect to M. <hi>Ley.</hi> Secondly, Some of them you name have written very little, ſo little, that no great ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is to be expected from them in any point. And thirdly, Some of them are erroneous dogmatiſts, of no more learning or authority then your ſelf. Fourthly, in your liſt of Divines you bring in M. <hi>Prinne,</hi> who is by his profeſſion not a Divine, but a Lawyer, (though I confeſſe he hath more divinity in him then divers of thoſe you have named with him:) But with what face can you bring him in, as on your ſide rather then on the Presbyterians, who hath written ſo much, and ſo emphatically againſt the Independents? and in that he wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth concerning the Sacrament, wherein he and the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians are at difference, it is as much againſt the Independent opinion and practice as theirs, and more too, though ſuch be their ſubtilty in that, as well as in other things, that wherein the Presbyterians and they agree, they will not joyn with them, becauſe they would have all the offence of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite party to fall upon the Presbyterian party alone, and none upon themſelves.</p>
               <p>Next after your Catalogue, you fall upon the Appendix, <hi>pag</hi> 4. and come to it again, <hi>pag.</hi> 10, 11. where I will take what you ſay into conſideration, and will anſwer to both. And then you bring in a Breviat of M. <hi>Leys</hi> two Epiſtles, and make an Anſwer to them; in which ſince what is in the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113626:10"/>Breviat is comprehended, they may both receive ſatisfaction at once</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Your Anſwer to the Epiſtle, <hi>pag.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>J. S.</p>
               <p n="1">1. You bring in M. <hi>Ley, deſiring the Gentlemen to whom he dedicates his Book, to counſell you not to cry down the government:</hi> To this you Anſwer by a Queſtion: <hi>Are you in ſuch fear of your government, that you make friends to me to be ſilent? is it ſo weak that it may be cried down?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You blame M. <hi>Ley</hi> for repeating what he hath ſaid, when you put a neceſſity upon him ſo to do, by your miſunderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or miſapplying of his ſpeeches, as in this particular: He out of pity to ſee you ſo ill imployed, as he profeſſeth towards the end of his Epiſtle Dedicatory, <hi>intreated the Gentlemen</hi> to whom he dedicated his book, <hi>to bestow ſome of their diſcreet counſels upon you, for better imployment of your parts and pen, then</hi> (he ſaith not in diſputing down, but) <hi>in crying down that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline and government as terrible and tyrannicall, which the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Senatours of both the Honourable Houſes of Parliament in part have ſet up and further endeavour to advance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By crying down here cannot reaſonably be meant a vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous oppoſition, but a clamorous contradiction; eſpecially ſince it is of a private perſon, as you are, againſt that which is ſet up by publike authority. But you, bringing in the ſpeech to the topicke of your ſelf-conceit, would have it imply ſome maſterfull power in your pen, before which the Presbytery cannot ſtand; You thinke, as by the parable of the flye on the wheel, you raiſe all the duſt in the motion, when your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance in polemicks is ſo poor and impotent, that if the Independent party had no other agents for it then you, it would quickly turn from a terrour (as to ſome it is, becauſe of the braggs and threats of ſome armed Sectaries) to a very ſcorn, as is ſaid of the ſythed chariots in the <hi>Ignatian Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave:</hi> Therefore I pray you, Sir, cry ſtill againſt the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian cauſe, be the Independent poſthorſe, to ſcrible againſt the Presbyterians every day; in the confidence of your
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113626:10"/>puiſſance, take ſo much boldneſſe and inſolence upon you, as to provoke the ableſt champions, yea a whole <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of learned and venerable Divines to be your An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>goniſts; (though I beleeve you cannot provoke them ſo much as may make them to take any notice of ſo weak and worthleſſe an adverſary) go on as you have begun, to make your ſelf a liti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> with <hi>your hand againſt every man,</hi> untill <hi>every mans hand be againſt you;</hi> and it will never trouble M. <hi>Ley,</hi> (but in Chriſtian compaſſion to you, and zeal to the truth) that you vent the vanity of your ſpirit, and bewray either your ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance or ill conſcience in ſuch conteſtations.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>That no Preſbytery parochiall,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>aſſumes ſuch power as the Prelaticall:</hi> To which you anſwer by another Queſtion; <hi>Is Preſbytery, becauſe Parochiall, Claſſicall, Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall leſſe Tyrannicall then Epiſcopacy, becauſe many rule in that, in this but one, or rather not more tyrannicall, becauſe one tyrant was not ſo much as many together, evil in a community is ſtronger and more diffuſive then in unity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where is your ingenuity, M. <hi>Saltmarſh,</hi> or your ſincerity in this allegation and Anſwer? I appeal to the Reader, (if but of ordinary apprehenſion, and not wholly poſſeſſed with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent prejudice) whether in the Epiſtle Dedicatory, <hi>pag.</hi> 2, 3, 4. there be not ſo much evidence brought in clearly contradictory to your conceit, as might have prevented the exception you make, and may preſently remove it upon the reading of M. <hi>Leys</hi> obſervations on that behalfe; whereto there needeth no other addition, ſave the Engliſh of a little of <hi>Seneca</hi> his Latin, quoted in the margin of the fourth page, which is, that <hi>Cyrus</hi> by dividing the river <hi>Gyndes</hi> (which in its full ſtream drowned a white horſe of his that drew his chariot (to which the Epiſcopall Sea may be compared) into 360 chanels, meant to make it paſſable by women on foot, and did ſo; ſuch is the Diviſion of Eccleſiaſticall power into a plurality of Presbyters, which being ſo leſſened and limited as they are like to be, are more like a dried chanel, then a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring floud.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:113626:11"/>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>If the Queſtion were rightly stated,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Is not the Queſtion of the Preſbytery yet ſtated?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is not rightly ſtated by all that meddle with the matter? and though it be rightly ſtated by the Aſſembly, that's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to common information; unleſſe the debates, reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and proofs of the Aſſembly therein were printed, which might be to the advancement of the truth, and great ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of many, both Miniſters and people thorowout the whole Kingdom, and I doubt not will be ſo, when the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will be pleaſed to permit them to be publike, which without their leave the Aſſembly may not doe.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, That <hi>I ſhould reſtore ſuch Tythes, if unlawfull, as I formerly received, becauſe the ſinne till then is not remitted,</hi> you ſay, <hi>I have done it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If ſo, there is more errour in your underſtanding, in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaking the tenure of Tythes, then in your conſcience, for this particular.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But take heed,</hi> ſay you, <hi>how you put forgiveneſſe of ſinne upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, for that is not only Popery, but like the Pape you would ſell pardons only to the rich, and none to the poor, and you would put more upon ſacrifice then upon mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though forgiveneſſe be not ſet upon reſtitution, yet is it not therefore not requiſite to Chriſtian juſtice, but neceſſary either in fact, where a man is able, or in affection, where he is not: and this doctrine is as meet for a poor man as a rich; and M. <hi>L.</hi> cited the ſaying of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his fifth Epiſtle <hi>ad Macedon.</hi> as many learned Divines have done before him; and ſo have they cited the example of <hi>Zacheus,</hi> Luk. 19.8. to the ſame purpoſe; but take you heed you do not condemn Chriſtianity for Popery. The Papiſts were wont to blaſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Proteſtant Truth, with the name of <hi>hereſie:</hi> the profane
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113626:11"/>uſed to reproach the piety of the firſt Table by the name of <hi>Puritaniſme;</hi> and many Sectaries, now adaies, brand many duties of juſtice and charity, which are branches of the ſecond Table, by the name of Popery; and you are one that miſapplieth that terme as much as any.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, You ſay, <hi>I would have men beleeve as they liſt, I would only have men not forced to beleeve as others liſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>M. <hi>Ley</hi> ſaid in the laſt page but one of his Epiſtle Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, that he was ſorry to ſee you ſo <hi>unſetled in your judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo ſedulous to prepare a patronage for all wilde and wicked fancies, that every one may beleeve what he liſt.</hi> The fault M. <hi>Ley</hi> findes with you, is not that you held forth ſuch a licentious faith, (nor on the contrary can he acquit you of ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit) but that your apologizing for all ſorts of Sectaries, as you do, would prepare a patronage for ſuch a latitude of belief.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, <hi>That he was wiſhed rather to a ſilent neglect of me, then to a loud conqueſt over me; Truth is not conquered when the man is trampled upon; It is not your being great can make you a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour, no more then your calling by Biſhops a true Preſbyter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The former part of this paragraph in <hi>theſi</hi> is true, in <hi>hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſi</hi> falſe, as the parts are applied to M. <hi>L.</hi> and you; for neither is truth on your ſide, nor any greatneſſe on his ſet to oppoſe it, or to domineer over it. For the later part, it is anſwered before.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, That he had rather confute <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> then my new-ſprung notions. And for <hi>your deſire rather to deal with</hi> Bellarmine <hi>then me, I did not thinke I had been ſo formidable an enemy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the Reader look upon the place in M. <hi>Leys</hi> Epiſtle, <hi>pag.</hi> 2. he will ſee that he took you rather for a contemptible,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113626:12"/>then a formidable enemy; and though you monopolize truth to your cauſe, he chargeth you, in the ſame place, with holding old errour under the name and notion of new truth.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>To the eighth: <hi>Nor am I leſſe a disputant in Divinity becauſe against forms of art and Logick, as you ſay.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>M. <hi>Ley</hi> ſaith nothing of that, but what your ſelf hath ſaid, and he cited your own words out of your book, <hi>viz.</hi> your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed diſlike of <hi>Logick, forms of art, and methods of reaſon,</hi> and renouncing of <hi>prudence, and conſequences, as the great engines of will-worſhip,</hi> for which he cited, <hi>pag.</hi> 16. and 60. of your book of <hi>Smoke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I may dispute in Chriſts ſchool, though refuſed in the ſchool of Tyrannus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I thinke, Sir, you know little of the ſchool of <hi>Tyrannus,</hi> but as a Divinity ſchool, wherein <hi>Paul</hi> the great Doctor of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians diſputed daily in the cauſe of Chriſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.9. And if it were a ſchool of Philoſophy before, (as it is like it was) you are ſuch an artiſt in Philoſophy, that you ſay <hi>interminis,</hi> if M. <hi>Ley</hi> will challenge you in any point of Philoſophy, you will not refuſe him in Logick, or forms of art; where in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect you challenge him to diſpute; which the Learned will look upon as a bragge, and it may be alſo a <hi>boaſting of a falſe gift,</hi> Prov. 25.14. that is, faſly boaſting of a gift which you have not; and it M. <hi>Ley</hi> refuſe either to make, or entertain a challenge with you in matter of Philoſophy, it will not (by any competent Judges) be conceived that he hath any cauſe to fear, but rather to ſcorn a monomachie with you in that kinde, ſince his learning in Philoſophy hath been eminently witneſſed by his Lectures on the whole firſt chapter of <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> which divers Learned men have earneſtly deſired for the Preſſe, and hope to ſee their deſires ſatisfied therein in time convenient.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:113626:12"/>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They are formes only for the wiſdom of men, not of God; nor dare I make my diſcoveries of Chriſt from reaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You mean that matters of Religion (which all of them have reference to Chriſt ſome way or other) ſhould not be ſet forth in forms of art, nor managed with any mixture of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or dictates of reaſon.</p>
               <p>A Learned man, and converſant in Scripture (as you would ſeem to be) may, if he ſeriouſly minde and marke it, obſerve in it (beſides the principall theme and ſcope of it, Divinity) much both of Logick and Philoſophy; I could give you ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inſtances of both, but I may not meaſure by the long ell (as <hi>Comminaeus</hi> calls the pike) while you manage the quarrell with a bodkin.</p>
               <p>And whereas you ſay, <hi>you dare not take any diſcoveries of Chriſt from reaſon.</hi> You might know by Scripture, that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion diſdains not diſcoverie of ſenſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.34. (much leſſe of reaſon) concerning Chriſt, as is clearly evidenced, <hi>Job.</hi> 21.29. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.3, 9. <hi>Acts</hi> 9.3, 4, 5, 1 Ep. <hi>John</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. And of both reaſon and ſenſe the Proteſtants make very good uſe againſt the Papiſts, as in many other particulars (which are to be ſeen in the book of Martyrs, and <hi>Chamierus Paustratia Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica</hi>) ſo eſpecially in the point of tranſubſtantiation; and is there not a diſcovery of Chriſt by ſenſe in the Sacraments, where by outward and viſible ſignes and ſeales, his inviſible graces ateropreſented unto us? And do not you your ſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to prove the Goſpel to be undeniably the word of God, without miracles, to aſſure us of the particular duties in it? and are not your proofs taken from topicks of reaſon? you cannot deny it, and if you do<note n="*" place="margin">Smoke of the Temple, <hi>pag.</hi> 20, 21, 22, 23.</note> your own papers will reprove you to your face; teſtimonies of the Ancients, though you ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly or inconſiderately begin your Catalogue of witneſſes with a Counterfeit Authout and Treatiſe, <hi>viz. Dionyſ. Areo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagim de divinis nominibus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I allow learning in its place, any where in the Kingdom
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113626:13"/>of the world, but not in the Kingdome of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is no great matter what you allow or allow not, unleſſe your learning were more, your judgement ſounder, &amp; your dealing more ſincere. But if there were any weight in your word, it would be prejudiciall, &amp; diſadvantagious to Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; would gratify the adverſaries of the truth, who by the Arts, Philoſophy, &amp; other ſecular learning in ſound Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, may be more ſoundly confuted in their errours againſt the Chriſtian Religion; and thus many of the Ancient Fathers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of them, as<note n="a" place="margin">Clem. Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and. ſtrom.</note> 
                  <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Orig.</hi> l. 1. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Homil. 31. <hi>in Lucam.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Origen,</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Obryſoſt.</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. 3. <hi>in Epiſt. ad Titum.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom,</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieron.</hi> Ep. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Hieron.</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Auguſt. de Doctrin. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. <hi>l. 2. c. 40.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine, &amp;</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Hieron. <hi>Ep. 14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Hierom,</hi> compareth the uſe of them in this way to the cutting off <hi>Goliahs</hi> head with his owne ſword, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.11. &amp;<note n="g" place="margin">Auguſt. ubi ſupra.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> to the ſpoyling of the Egyptians, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.36. This the ſubtle Apoſtate <hi>Iuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> knew well enough, &amp; therefore in craft &amp; ſpight he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad the inſtruction of the Children of Chriſtians in the arts and literature of the heathens, as<note n="h" place="margin">Ammian, Marcell n. Rerum geſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. <hi>lib. 22. &amp; 25.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ammianus Marcellinus</hi> both obſerves and cenſures, as an unjuſt edict, though but an heathen by religion, and a ſouldier by profeſſion.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>page.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>The ninth. <hi>For my being an ubiquitary in beliefe, and your proofe of this from the ſeverall opinions ſtated in my booke, Can you bee ſo unfaithfull to that Booke? can you, who would bee counted an orthodox and a Divine, thus force and compell thoſe opinions upon mee, or rather upon the paper onely where they are printed? becauſe I ſtated the opinions of men, am I therefore a man of all thoſe opinions? The beſt is, the world may convince you of this, and of my purpoſe in that. And now you are thus unfaithfull in a little, I may ſuſpect you for more. Are you one of thoſe who pretend to be in the mount with God to give laws for religion? Can we truſt you in the more excellent myſteries of the Father, while you trifle thus and deceive the Brethren?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What a piece of exaggerating Rhetorike is here, to ſmoke over M. <hi>Leys</hi> ſincerity with a ſuſpition of ſuch prevarication, as is but too frequent in your owne practice, not at all in his?
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113626:13"/>and if any heterodox conceipts be caſt upon you, which are not yours, you may thank your ſelfe, for you ſet downe oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Tenets ſo ambiguouſly, that it is hard to ſay what opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons you owne among them; and therefore M. <hi>Ley</hi> ſpake of them with words of caution, <hi>as</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 3. of his Epiſtle to your ſelfe.</note> 
                  <hi>you ſeeme to me,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>In your exceptions againſt Preſbytery, and I muſt rather take your Tenet to be againſt, then among the Preſbyterian poſitions,</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Ibid. <hi>pag.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>In the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of Independency you deliver downright Anabaptiſme, without any word of exception, or caution to your Reader.</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Ibid. <hi>pag.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Such opinions as thoſe, which you ſeeme rather to confirme then to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute.</hi> And if any man take you for a favourer of ſuch erroneous Tenets as you repeat without a word of refutation or reproofe, is it not your owne fault rather then his? your courting of all ſects, and compliance with them, might juſtly occaſion a ſuſpition of your unſoundnes in R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ligion.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>page.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>That I am an Antinomian, and deale with ſome late Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines as ſome with Luther;</hi> and hereof you ſeeke to purge your ſelfe by aſſerting ſome ſentences of Scripture, which you thinke may cleare you from Antinomianiſme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But that will not ſerve your turne, the accuſation is lately ſet cloſer upon you, by a<note n="e" place="margin">M <hi>Gataker</hi> in his late Booke againſt M. <hi>Sal.</hi> called, <hi>A miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take or miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved.</hi>
                  </note> Reverend Divine of the Aſſembly, then that you can ſhake it off by ſo poore an Apology; and for that layd to your charge by M. <hi>Ley,</hi> what anſwer do you make? none but ſuch an one as aggravates your guilt, by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one falſhood upon the ſhoulder of another, whereby it becomes the more conſpicuous; for you ſay, <hi>you have not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoted any.</hi> Have you not, Sir, when you have ſo cited one part of an Author for your ſenſe, and left out the next words, which clearly for forth his judgement in contradiction to your opinion? Have you not done ſo by M. <hi>S. Bolton?</hi> were you not plainly convinced of it by M. <hi>Ley</hi> in his epiſtle to you? and yet you ſhew not a ſpark of ingenuity, or grace, in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging your witting and wilfull falſe dealing in that allegation; but waſh your hands with <hi>Pilate</hi> (as if you were innocent) and ſpit the reproaches in his face, which juſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto your owne.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:113626:14"/>
               <p>You ſay, as by way of excuſe, and (which is more, and worſe) by way of juſtification of your ſelfe, <hi>That you but ſingled out that truth from many in one leafe, before they ſpoyled it in the next, and like Pilate, who, aſking onely what truth was, would not tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by it, but departed.</hi> And doe not you (Pilate-like againe) turne away from the truth of a Teſtimony, when you admit of part to ſerve your turne, and reject another part, though contiguous unto it, becauſe it is contrary to your Tenet?</p>
               <p>Amongſt other flouriſhes of falſhood, you ſay, that M. <hi>L.</hi> and his aſſociated Brethren pretend themſelves to be in the mount, to give lawes for religion; where finde you this? how can you prove it? did you ever read it in any of their writings, or heare it from their lips? I am ſure you did not: how then can you object it? have you the inſpection of their hearts? If you take that upon you, you have got above fifteene cubits higher, then the top of <hi>Sinai,</hi> or <hi>Horeb,</hi> even to Gods tribunall, by whom alone the hearts of all men are to be judged.</p>
               <p>And for that you ſay, <hi>of making lawes for religion,</hi> you know they have no power, nor doe they take any upon them, ſave onely by way of humble advice to preſent the reſult of their debates, and votes to the Parliament, concerning ſuch matters as from either of the Honourable houſes are ſent unto them.</p>
               <p>And now, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, to pay you in your owne coyne, and returne your owne words upon you, <hi>Can you bee ſo unfaithfull to that Booke, can you who would be counted an orthodox Divine,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened above the meaſure of other Miniſters, ſo groſſely falſify ſo plaine, and perſpicuous a ſentence? <hi>The beſt is, the world</hi> (while his Booke and your Pamphlet are extant) <hi>may convince you in this, and now you are thus unfaithfull in a little</hi> (or rather in much) <hi>J may ſuſpect you for more. Can we truſt you in the more excellent myſteries of the Father, while you trifle thus, and deceive the Brethren? page.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>J. S: <hi>page.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That J am unſtable,</hi> To the eleventh. <hi>For my unſtableneſſe, if to bee ſometimes darknes, and now light in the Lord, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will put off this to another place, where I ſhall have occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113626:14"/>to bring it in, that I may not trouble the Reader with a needleſſe repetition of the ſame paſſage.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>page.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>To the twelfth. <hi>Nor doe I glory, I hope, in the quicke diſpatch of what I doe; but doe not you as well over-deliberate, as I over-diſpatch, and glory in that?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whether you glory in quick diſpatch or no let the Reader judge, upon evidence produced to that purpoſe. <hi>page.</hi> 11. 12. of M. <hi>Leys</hi> Epiſtle to you; but you cannot object the like of his deliberations, ſince he hath not told his Reader how long he was about any Book, as you have done how ſhort a time you took for yours. For that you ſpeake in diſparagement of humane learning, it is an old humour of the Anabaptiſts, who at firſt rejected all Books but the Bible, and after that grew ſo wiſe as to be religious enough without that alſo, and laſt of all they came to blaſpheme that bleſſed Book, as a dead let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and a beggerly element; and ſuch proficients are ſome of our ſublimated ſectaries.</p>
               <p>But however you ſlight all ſecular learning, you muſt not aſſume to your ſelf, or your party, (as you ſeeme to doe) a propriety either of intereſt, or exerciſe in the word, or ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, or power of Chriſt, wherein thoſe whom you looke upon with an oblique ſpirit have as good right, and as fair evidence as thoſe of your party, who take upon them to be moſt ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall. For that you conclude withall, concerning the brewer, in a forme of affected gravity, ſaying, <hi>I deſire not to ſhew ſo much of the old man or former corruptions, as to ſparkle ſo lightly with you.</hi> Me thinks you ſhould haue brought in a young man, rather then an old man, ſo lightly ſparkling as will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come your gravity to anſwer him. Or if you meane by the <hi>old man,</hi> that part of humane nature, which remaines unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate, that (though you may intend a reproach upon ſenio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of yeares) may be, and for the moſt part is more predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant in a young man then in an old, as M. <hi>Ley</hi> hath obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the tenth Section of his laſt Book againſt you.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:113626:15"/>
               <p>J. S. <hi>page.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>To the thirteenth, <hi>My interpoſing being no delay to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, as you ſay, why then do you call my Booke a</hi> Remora, <hi>and ſay my Quere was to retard the government? I pray you now be friends with your ſelf,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No doubt he is ſo, and ſo was, when he wrote thoſe words, for you might intend your Book and Querie for a <hi>Remora,</hi> and yet it might, and I hope it will prove otherwiſe. Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and events are many times very contrarie, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſayd to his Brethren, You thought evil againſt me, but God meant it unto good, to bring to paſſe as at this day, to ſave much peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple alive, <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.20.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>page.</hi> 7. 8.</p>
               <p>To the fourteenth, <hi>That he may be better imployed then in writing; they are your friends indeed that wiſh ſo, you cannot be worſe imployed then in ſpeaking evil of your Brethren, in advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your ſelves, Lording it over the heritage, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As you have often ſet upon the Presbyterians with ſuch ſlanders, ſo you have beene<note n="e" place="margin">See light for ſmoke Sect. 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 13. &amp;c &amp; Sect. 18. <hi>pag.</hi> 51. 52. and Sect 19 <hi>pag</hi> 54. &amp;c.</note> often anſwered both directly, and by way of juſt recrimination; which may be a ſuperſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deas for my further Reply in this place.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For others undertaking me, as many as pleaſe, for I feare not an hoſt, nor a multitude of penmen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You are ſo bold all men may ſee, (ſome unmannerly fellow haply would ſay, ſo impudent) that you dare contend with many together, who taken ſingle were able to cruſh you in any encounter that is to be managed with learning and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie; and after the rate you write, you need not care how many you undertake, nor they neither, who are undertaken by you, ſince you doe but with an impotent malignity nibble at the heele, when you give them faire opportunity to break your head, unleſſe they chooſe rather to kicke you off with ſcorne, then to make a ſerious and ſetled buſines of combating with you.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:113626:15"/>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 8. and 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſumme of M.</hi> Leys <hi>treatiſe and Anſwer to it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You have an excellent faculty firſt in contracting, then in contradicting and confuting, your adverſarie; for you have reduced the ſumme of M. <hi>Leys</hi> Booke of ſeventeene ſheets to leſſe then a ſingle page, and confuted them all, as you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, in leſſe then a leaf; would it not bee fit ſuch an able and nimble champion as you are ſhould be ſet upon thoſe great An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian <hi>Goliahs, Baronius, Bellarm. Suarez, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſques?</hi> how would you enervate, and ſhrinke up their many vaſt and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulent volumes into a poor, dry, and ſapleſſe ſckeleton? O for <hi>Bellarminus enervatus</hi> of your compoſing! That of <hi>Ameſius</hi> to it would be but as a rude ſteeple clock to a moſt curious pock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et watch. But to the particulars.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>That the graduall ſubordination of Aſſemblies is made good by M. <hi>Rutherford. Is this reaſoning, or reference? and this you have done all along, referred us either o your ſelfe, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to anſwere for you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>L. M.</p>
               <p>Vpon your finding fault with claſſicall, provinciall, and Nationall Aſſemblies as no wholeſome words, M.<note n="f" place="margin">Light for ſmoke, <hi>page.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Ley</hi> told you, that the graduall ſubordination of Aſſemblies, againſt the Independency of Congregationall meetings, was made good by a large and learned Book of M. Samuel <hi>Rutherford;</hi> of which reference I ſee not what may offend you, unleſſe your idleneſſe miſlike the word <hi>large,</hi> and your ignorance the word <hi>learned,</hi> for it is an uſuall and commendable courſe of many worthy writers, for the husbanding of time, that they may not <hi>actum agere,</hi> to make references for ſatisfaction to larger Treatiſes then the preſent occaſion will permit. And to finde fault with M. <hi>Ley</hi> for this, ſhewes you rather a wran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gler then a Reader.</p>
               <p>But whereas you ſay, that he hath dens ſo all along, it is not your unwitting miſtake, which might eaſily be pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but your wilfull ſlander, which you ſhould heartily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113626:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:113626:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:113626:17"/>of; and of this I doubt not but there are as many witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as there be ingenuous and conſcientious Readers of his Booke and your looſe ſheets. And I dare challenge you, on his behalfe, to make proofe of any one reference, either to his owne Books, or any other, for which there was not juſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion given, approvable in the judgement of judicious men. And if references come too often, it is moſt like to be your owne fault, whoſe importunate, or impertinent iterations of the ſame particulars put him to it.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That your Preſbyteries are not ſo ſingular, more free, conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, more peaceable, more Apostolicall, more authorized then other Churches;</hi> and then you ſay, <hi>theſe are good commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but had half ſo much been proved by the word, your govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had paſſed before this.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here you put him to a neceſſity of reference to his firſt Book, (unleſſe he ſhould make a needleſſe repetition of a whole ſection,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. <hi>pag.</hi> 11, 12, 13.</note> to confute your cavill) where he hath given full and cleare evidence, (ſuch as no rationall man can deny) how Claſſicall, Provinciall, and Nationall Aſſemblies are more warrantable then the gathered Churches of Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 8, 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That Tithes are spoken against by thoſe that ſcruple not at ſlander, or ſacriledge, that they uſurp upon God, and his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters that alienate them from his worſhip and ſervice.</hi> Having made this the ſummary of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Ley</hi> his eighth ſection, you adde as an Anſwer to it; <hi>For that of ſacriledge and uſurpation upon God in alienating Tithes, never did Prelate, no nor Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> Mountague <hi>plead an higher Title for Tithes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You had condemned Tithes <hi>as Popiſh and Jewiſh undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Smoke, pag. <hi>25.</hi>
                  </note> which gave M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Ley</hi> occaſion to ſpeak the more fully and freely in the refutation of your over-confident aſſertion; yet did he not advance the Tenure of Tithes above that which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Nye</hi> (a Claſſicall Authour with you, though againſt the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113626:17"/>authority of claſſes) hath affirmed of them, and he named him to you, yet you are ſilent concerning him, and take up a clamour againſt M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Ley,</hi> as more Jewiſh and Popiſh then a Prelate, yea then Biſhop <hi>Mountague:</hi> what partiality is this?</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What, ſacriledge and uſurpation to deny Tithes? Where are you, in the Covenant or no? is it not a Parliament Ordinance you take them by? Will you ſet up a divine right over that now? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they may juſtly now withdraw their Ordinance for Tithes, and leave you to your Divine right, and ſee what the people will pay you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>M. <hi>Ley</hi> did not call it ſacriledge to deny Tithes,<note place="margin">Light for ſmoke, pag <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> though it may be true, but ſaid, <hi>there was a clamour taken up against them by ſuch as made no conſcience, either of ſlander or of ſacriledge;</hi> and ſuch are many worldly Mammoniſts, and erroneous Dogmatiſts: and what is this to the Covenant?</p>
               <p>And to that you ask, <hi>is it not a Parliament Ordinance you take them by?</hi> It may be acknowledged with humble thanks to the Parliament, that their Ordinance is an help to recover the right of Tithes; but the right of Tithes is much more ancient then that Ordinance; for there are many ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes that entitle Miniſters to them, and allow them to ſue for them by courſe of Law: nor will the opinion of divine right in ſome, be ſufficient ground to abrogate the payment of Tithes to all, though you would cry down their Tenure, to fright the conſcientious out of their duty, to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the covetous in their parſimony, and all to ſcrue up your own penſions to the higher proportion. Becauſe while they are to pay Tithes, as of right, to Parochiall Paſtours, there will be the leſſe latitude in the matter, and leſſe light ſomnes in the man to make an allowance of courteſy to content you their Independent Doctours. But enough of this. I had thought to have made none Anſwer, but a reference to the eighth ſection of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Leys</hi> Book, which is well worth the reading, and ſufficient of it ſelf for your full refutation.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:113626:18"/>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To that of your commending old men and age, I reverence age, but not the old man in them; and for dreams being more excellent then viſions, it is a curious ſpeculation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Vpon your preferring young men ſo much before old men, as to ſay, <hi>ſurely we may more ſafely hearken to the younger, that ſee viſions of Reformation, then to the elder, that dream dreams of it only.</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Ley</hi> made an elaborate compariſon, and reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of both in the tenth ſection of his Book, from <hi>pag.</hi> 23. to the 28. incluſively, which I dare commend to the peruſall of any judicious Reader, and doubt not but he will think M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Saltmarſh</hi> ſhould not have mentioned it without appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the diſcourſe, and thanks to the Authour.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why are you ſo much in defence of jesting, and ſo ſerious in your Scripture proofs for it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>L. M.</p>
               <p>Becauſe you carped at him more then once for a pleaſant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe of your miſapplication of Scripture, which gave him juſt occaſion to ſhew how, and in what caſes a taunting ſpeech may be allowed, which he hath ſo done, <hi>Sect.</hi> 15. <hi>pag.</hi> 39. <hi>&amp;c</hi> that the moſt Readers, (your Life for one) may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive inſtruction by his diſcourſe, and ſo be engaged to be gratefull to him, not reproachfull, as you are.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And for other Church-governments not coming under the triall of Parliament, nor coming out by sheir Authority,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the Reader pleaſe to compare M. <hi>Leys</hi> nineteenth Section (wherein the Independents and Presbyterians are compared for modeſty, and humility,) with this paragraph, marked with the number ſix, he will caſily perceive how feeble, and frivolous a Reply this is, to that which M. <hi>Ley</hi> hath written. And the like conviction he may meet withall, if he take into comparative conſideration M. <hi>S.</hi> his next paragraph of goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell-governments, <hi>pag.</hi> 10. and M. <hi>Leyes</hi> 21 Section, from <hi>pag.</hi> 60 to <hi>pag.</hi> 63.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:113626:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus far</hi> for your Anſwer to M. <hi>Leyes,</hi> which is ſuch a one, ſo ſhort, ſo ſlight, ſo falſe, and yet to a ſilly and partiall reader ſo Fallacious, that he that reads both will finde cauſe to marvel that a pretender to wit ſhould deale ſo weakly, and to grace, ſo wickedly in a cauſe of this kinde.</p>
               <p>That which next followeth in M. <hi>S.</hi> his pamphlet, is the Teſtimony of <hi>Salmaſius,</hi> which being heterogeneal from all the reſt, I will aſſigne to the laſt place, as he did in his former an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, where that cometh in as a Poſtſcript, and concludeth the Booke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:113626:19"/>
               <head>M. S. his cauſeleſſe and unchriſtian reproach of M. <hi>Ley,</hi> taken (without oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion given) out of <hi>C. D.</hi> his <hi>Defence of</hi> M. <hi>L.</hi> printed with his Book of <hi>Light for Smoke,</hi> brought in in this manner.</head>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>C. D. his Treatiſe printed with M.</hi> Leys <hi>Book, in M.</hi> Leys <hi>commendation, whether made by himſelf or ſome other he beſt knowes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>L. M.</p>
               <p>VVHether it were made by himſelfe, or ſome other, it was not made againſt you, but againſt a ſcurrilous Newſmonger, as the Title ſheweth, and therefore herein you meddle where you ſhould not, and deſerve to ſuffer <hi>as a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body in other mens matters.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.15. And you make it your buſines to reproach M. <hi>Ley,</hi> as if he were vainglorious, in five particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In affecttaion of Titles.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In mentioning of his Books printed and to be printed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In printing an honourable Anagram made upon his Name.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In giving the ſignification of his Name in Hebrew and Spaniſh.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In publiſhing ſome letters written in his commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Whereto I ſhall returne you Anſwer, 1. <hi>In generall,</hi> and then 2. <hi>In particular.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In generall,</hi> I ſay you have dealt very foully and unfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly herein, in that you have concealed from your Reader the <hi>occaſion,</hi> and ſcope for which thoſe particulars (ſelected by you out of the Treatiſe) were brought in; <hi>which</hi> was, not ſo
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113626:19"/>much for commendation of M. <hi>Ley,</hi> as for neceſſary vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him from notorious contempt, put upon him in the Newsbook of that contumelious Scribler; who beginneth thus with him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There came out this day a Book of</hi> 106 <hi>pages, written by John</hi> Ley, <hi>ſo is the Title, whether it was of the Lees French or Spaniſh, J Leave it to others to enquire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon theſe words <hi>[So is the Title]</hi> C. D. tells him, <hi>that in the Title page of M.</hi> Ley <hi>his Book he might have knowne him as one of the Aſſembly of Divines; and if he had enquired as the Aſſembly of what account he was with his Reverend Brethren, he might have knowne that he was by them choſen, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And becauſe he made a diſgracefull deſcant on M. <hi>Leys</hi> name, the greek Epigram made on it and him (when he was Preſident of Syon Colledge, about an yeare and halfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) was in part repeated.</p>
               <p>This might be warrant enough for him to have righted himſelfe from ſuch reproach, by reporting any truth that might releive his reputation in that behalfe; which though with ſuch as knew him might be needleſſe, yet to moſt who knew him not it might be neceſſary, and as lawfull as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary: for,</p>
               <p>Though it be good advice which <hi>Solomon</hi> giveth, <hi>Let ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man praiſe theo, and not thine owne mouth a ſtranger, and not thine own lips;</hi> Pro. 27.2. (and the counſell holds as well in praiſe of the pen, as of the mouth,) yet when a man is injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly vilified, eſpecially a Miniſter of note, and publique em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, he may doe ſuch an act of juſtice and charity to his owne good Name, as well as to another mans.</p>
               <p>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> was as wiſe, as modeſt, as humble a Chriſtian as could be, and yet (when his adverſaries put him to it) he made his owne Apology, with comparative praiſe of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with others, and prelation above others; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16.22.23. and thoſe not only the falſe Apoſtles, who were emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of his glory, and envious at it, but he compares himſelfe with the cheif Apoſtles, ſaying, <hi>In nothing am I behinds the cheif Apoſtles,</hi> 2 Cor. 12.11. and tells the <hi>Cariuthiaus,</hi> to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113626:20"/>whom he wrot, that he <hi>ought to have been commended by them,</hi> in the ſame place.</p>
               <p>If then M. <hi>Ley</hi> had written that of himſelfe, which you mention as an immodeſt vindication, it being true, and utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it upon juſt occaſion, and had owned it in his owne name, he had not for that deſerved either reproach or reproofe from you, or any one elſe; and if he did it with concealment of his name, he had the warrant of the ſame Apoſtle for that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealment, who, when he ſpake of his rapture into the third heaven, and his hearing words unſpeakable, which was a matter of glory, brought it in as in a third perſon. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. v. 4.5.6.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whereas you ſay<note n="a" place="margin">Pag. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>that he who ſpeaks ſo much in M.</hi> Ley <hi>his praiſe, ſtands a little too neere him;</hi> I muſt tell you you are a man of ſmall reading, if you have not met with ſome ſcores of Authors, of good account, who have printed with their owne Books <hi>elogia</hi> or laudatory Prefaces, or poems of other men; not as C. <hi>D.</hi> came in, on the back ſide of M. <hi>Ley</hi> his book, when all was done, but in, or very neer the frontiſpice, that they might come firſt in view, and be moſt like to be read, what ever was not.</p>
               <p>And though your example be of little worth and weight for Anſwere to another mans objection, yet againſt your ſelfe (as<note n="*" place="margin">Opinor tuum teſtimoniü quod in alienâre leve eſſet, id in tua, quum contra te eſt, graviſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum debet eſſe. <hi>Cicer. Orat.</hi> 1. <hi>pro</hi> P. <hi>Quintio pag.</hi> 13.</note> Cicero ſayd of <hi>Nevius,</hi> an unworthy and wicked fellow) it is ſufficient conviction; and your ſelfe have publiſhed a Book of verſes, with as high ſcrued commendation, both up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your ſelfe and them, in the next leafe before your Book begun, and next after your Epiſtle Dedicatory, as could be ſet before the Poem of <hi>Homer</hi> in Greek, or <hi>Virgil</hi> in Latine, <hi>Bartas</hi> in French, <hi>Quarles,</hi> or <hi>Sandis</hi> in Engliſh. Your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical Encomiaſtes cals your book<note n="*" place="margin">Eſt pius, eſt doctus, quod vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co, plura, tuus. In t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum non cerno corpore naevum. Ni naevus nae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buiſſe fiet. <hi>Pag. 13. 14.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>pious and learned,</hi> and makes as if it were the compendium of all prayſe to call it yours; and yet afterwards adds, that in the whole body of it he ſees not the leaſt mole, or freckle, or blemiſh, unleſſe it be a blemiſh to want a blemiſh. And yet, by his leave, your Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eticall Meditation on <hi>The Song of Songs</hi> deſerves to be chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, in the judgement of pious and judicious Criticks, for
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113626:20"/>ſome want on expreſſions of, heathen Poetry upon that ſacred <hi>Sonnet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And whereas M. <hi>Ley</hi> deſires no more of the Licenſers hand then a bare <hi>Imprimatur</hi> in the written Copy for his Book, you bring your Licenſer in print, with ſome ſolemne atteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, either of praiſe, or of Apology on your behalfe, witneſſe <hi>Jo. Bachilers</hi> approbation of your <hi>Smoke in the Temple, as more then ordinarily uſefull in thoſe times;</hi> and his aprobation of your laſt Pamphlet, or <hi>Letter to M.</hi> Ley, <hi>as agreeable to the laws of nature, and of grace;</hi> wherein they who impartially peruſe what is written on both ſides, will in the finall account re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve that he hath not ſo much honoured you, as ſhamed him ſelf.</p>
               <p>Thus much for Anſwer to the imputation <hi>in Generall,</hi> now for <hi>the particulars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 For the <hi>Titles</hi> you mention, there was juſt cauſe and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of their repetition, becauſe the malevolent New mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger brought in M. <hi>Ley</hi> as ſome obſcure and unworthy Levite, who was not knowne by any other Title then that which belonged to him from his baptiſme; whereas he might have ſeene in the Title page of his firſt book againſt you, that he was <hi>a member of the Aſſembly of Divines;</hi> and that being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, the other particular Titles, being all of them of uſe for repulſe of his contempt, occaſionally drew in one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and to a fellow of his condition the Anſwere was very ſutable, becauſe he was moſt capable of ſuch a conviction.</p>
               <p>But for M. <hi>Ley</hi> himſelf, he is ſo farre from a vain affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Titles of prelation, that when, many years ago, he was importuned by many great friends in the Vniverſity, and out of it, to take the degree of <hi>Doctour in Divinity,</hi> he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, upon this reaſon, (as many worthy witneſſes well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member) becauſe he was then in conteſtation with a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of his pariſh, with whom he deſired to be at peace, and he would not take ſuch a title, and degree upon him, as might perhaps provoke him to anger or envy, (though he were ſo Religious, that being dead he hopes he is in Heaven) by reaſon of the nominall preeminence, and perſonall prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113626:21"/>which (whether by right, or long-received cuſtom, or both, I cannot tell) is aſſigned to Theologicall graduates of that denomination.</p>
               <p>And for your ſcoffing cloſe, or concluſion of that titular objection, <hi>pag.</hi> 11. <hi>I remember not any of the Apoſtles in ſuch Offices and Titles;</hi> It is a very poor, and empty jeer. For,
<list>
                     <item>1. Many things have been, which you never read, nor heard of.</item>
                     <item>2. You remembred not that any one of them were ſtiled Academicall graduates, as either <hi>Batchelers,</hi> or <hi>Maſters of Art, Batchelers,</hi> or <hi>Doctours in Divinity, Profeſſours of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, Provoſts, Prefects of Colledges, Vice-chancellours:</hi> which titles you give to <hi>Henry Smith,</hi> to whom you dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate your book; and yet you will not ſay they are either to be denyed, or derided.</item>
                     <item>3. Nor do you remember, I am ſure, that any one of them played the Poets, nor took upon them the Title of <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Britannicus,</hi> and under that title minted, and vented news for popular Information, as (if good Intelligencers be not miſtaken) you have ſometimes done.</item>
                     <item>4. Your exception herein is but a negative teſtimoniall argument in a matter of no neceſſity, either of exiſtence, or cognizance.</item>
                     <item>5. There are many particulars wherein the Apoſtolicall times and after ages do not agree, and yet the diſſent is no fault on either ſide; of this you may read an Epiſtle of<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>Doctour</hi> Hall. <hi>5.</hi> Decad. of Epiſt. Ep. <hi>2.</hi> pag. <hi>164.</hi>
                        </note> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour <hi>Hall,</hi> before he was Biſhop, I ſay before he was Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop (that you may not ſtartle at the teſtimony, as if it were Antichriſtian) wherein he ſheweth by many inſtances, the difference of the preſent Church from the Apoſtolicall, and needleſnes of out conformity thereto in all things; to which obſervations of his it is eaſy to adde much more then he hath ſaid, to the ſame purpoſe.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond <hi>particular</hi> is, the <hi>mention of his books printed and to be printed;</hi> which ſerved to the ſame end, <hi>viz.</hi> further to confute the conceit of the ſcurtillous <hi>Novelliſt</hi> concerning
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113626:21"/>M. <hi>Ley,</hi> whom he ſo named, as to make his Reader believe he was a man unknown untill he appeared againſt his miſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming <hi>paſſages;</hi> wherein it is obſervable, that <hi>C. D.</hi> left out ſome books of M. <hi>L.</hi> partly printed, and partly licenſed for the Preſſe, and you (out of what motive you beſt know) leave out ſome which he hath mentioned. But to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation given of them, you ſay, <hi>give them leave to ſpeak them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in this point,</hi> pag. 11. If you mean this of the books, as you uſe that phraſe after wards, they have ſpoken as much as others ſay of them; if of the Readers, they will ſpeak or write their judgement of them, as ſome have done allready; whereof ſufficient proof may be produced, when juſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion requireth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The third Exception</hi> you take is, at the <hi>Anagram and Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gram on M.</hi> Ley <hi>his name,</hi> made when he was Preſident of <hi>Syon Colledge,</hi> about a year and an half age, which was in part Printed in Greek, as it was penned by one learned man, and rendred in Engliſh by another, (both Maſters of Art, and Divines of many years ſtanding) becauſe it very well ſerved to oppoſe the reproach of the Pamphleters Etymology, or rather pſeudology of his Name, from the Lets of wine, French or Spaniſh; but it was ſo contracted, and turned, by M. <hi>Leys</hi> direction, as might well have prevented M. <hi>S.</hi> his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation. For</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> The epigram conſiſted of twelve Greek verſes, and he would not ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er ſo much as two of them in the Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be printed.</p>
               <p>Secondly, He cauſed the ſecond verſe in Engliſh to be broken off, before the words—<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, becauſe he would not have them tranſlated, as ſpeaking more in his praiſe then his modeſty would admit.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, In that ſecond verſe be put out the word <hi>rare,</hi> and put in the word <hi>now,</hi> in ſtead of it; and ſo farre abated the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of that Epithete, as to make it no more thon ſuch an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition as might be applyed to any perſon, thing, or action, though as meane and contemptible as his adverſary, or his ſcandalous and ſcurrilous Queres put out againſt them.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:113626:22"/>
               <p>Fourthly, This modeſty hath been imputed to him as a fault from the hand of a learned Friend (who had a ſight of the verſes in a M <hi>S</hi>) with a requeſt that he would prefixe them entirely before the next Booke of his that commeth forth, and there is one ready for the Preſſe of his tranſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing) that words are part of a latine letter lately written to M. <hi>Ley,</hi> which for the learned Readers ſatiſfaction I have ſet in<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tinam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrum epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gramma ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctſset <hi>Novello maſtix</hi> (vir cruditus &amp; ingenioſus) nec ſolum diſtichon lectori donam, celaſset Illas laudes, quibus nemo te neſeen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, modò pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſit, &amp; Graeculus, non libentiſsimè ſubſcripſiſſet; etſi autem mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilumin praeſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ <hi>Novello<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſtix</hi> edide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit <hi>(quod tuo nimto mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiae tribuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt)</hi> ſore tamea non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpero ut perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum aliquando prodeat. Te<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> oratum habeo, ut libro tuo, quicunque fit quem proxime in lucem emit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, praefigere ne graveris <hi>Dated, April. 23. 1646.</hi>
                  </note> the margine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The fourth particular</hi> cavill is made at the <hi>ſignification of M.</hi> Leys <hi>name in Hebrew, the grace of God; and in Spaniſh, law:</hi> which was ſo pertinently brought in to confute that fond E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymologiſt, that being true, it could not with diſcretion have been omitted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The fifth note</hi> of vain boaſting implicitely imputed by you to M. <hi>L.</hi> is <hi>the recitall of ſome letters of commendation,</hi> pag. 19, 20, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where ſtill you conceal the occaſion with an unſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere ſubtlety, not becoming a Chriſtian, much leſſe a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Goſpel, leaſt of all one of ſo refined a Reformation as you pretend unto. The occaſion you know was this, The ſcurrilous novelliſt had ſuggeſted M. <hi>Leys</hi> book ſtuck up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on M. <hi>Meredith</hi> the Stationers hand, to his loſſe, and that therefore he was to make him a recompence, and this, with a ſenſles abſurdity too, he wrote for news of the ſame day when M. <hi>Leys</hi> book came out; which being made known to M. <hi>Meredith,</hi> he wrote a letter of confutation of that folly, and falſhood, and in that ſaid the book <hi>ſold very well,</hi> and that he had ſeverall Letters (from ſuch as were able to judge) in approbation of it, as worthy both to be bought and read; and he preſently ſent him that which came next to hand, the writer whereof, a godly and learned Divine, ſaith thus, <hi>I pray you preſent my reſpects to Reverend M.</hi> Ley, <hi>I bleſſe Gad for him, and for his learned and faithfull labours, especially his last in Anſwer to</hi> Saltmarſh <hi>his Query, and in vindication of the Cities and Miniſters Petition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this is all, Sir, you were pleaſed to remember of <hi>C. D.</hi> his <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> whereas there are many things in it of more weight, of which you ſeem to take no notice. Doubtleſſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113626:22"/>your intent was to caſt <hi>a dead fly</hi> of vain oſtentation <hi>into the ointment</hi> of his good name, that <hi>a little folly might cauſe a ſtinking ſavour on him, who is in reputation for wiſdom and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> Eccleſ. 10.1. and your motive to this (as it is to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) was envy at his approbation and praiſe, which made you rather point at the letters, then report their contents, or the occaſion of their writing and Printing.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus I have gathered up all in your book that concerns you materially, and your friend printed on the back ſide of yours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus I have gathered?</hi> Even ſo, Sir, as you gather Churches, with ſo little ſincerity, that all may gather by your dealing that you make no conſcience of ſcandalous ſuggeſtions, or of fraudulent reſervations.</p>
               <p>But if you dare be ſo bold with ſinne, me thinks you ſhould not be ſo blinde in judgement, as to think ſuch groſſe miſcarriage in the cauſe in difference can be ſecured with all the ſubtilty you have, from ſhamefull infamy.</p>
               <p>And I wiſh you did but hear what judicious and wiſe men, both Divines, and others, have ſaid of you, ſince they have read the reciprocall writings betwixt M. <hi>Ley</hi> and you. Truly, Sir, whatever you think of your ſelf, they take you (for ſuch gatherings and ſeverings as you make of clear and plain words) to be little better then ſalt that hath loſt its ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, good for nothing but to be troden under feet, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.13. and ſome of them who are men of note for pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and prudence, and who are ſo farre from conceiving you come off with credit in the cauſe, that they think you ſhould not go away without puniſhment, at leaſt that you cannot eſcape ſhame for your wilfull falſehood, and abuſe of your Reader.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And for other particulars more ſubſtantiall, your Bookes and mine are both abread, let them ſpeake for themſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:113626:23"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And why may they not ſpeake for themſelves in matters of leſſe moment, as well as more ſubſtantiall? but whether for ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or both, M. <hi>Ley</hi> deſires nothing more, then that all who read the one would read the other. But you cannot without hypocriſy pretend ſo much ſyncerity, when you doe all you can to delude your Reader by ſubtile concealments, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intimations; and make it a fault in M. <hi>Ley,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In the firſt page of your letter to M. <hi>Ley.</hi>
                  </note> fairly and freely to informe the Reader of ſuch alternate paſſages betwixt him &amp; you, as make for the clearing of the difference betwixt you.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Readers muſt now judge in the ſpirit, what we both have written in the Letter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What you meane by <hi>the ſpirit</hi> I know not; I doubt you meane ſome new, giddy, wavering fancy, ſuch as ſets you on ſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling you care not what. But if they will, as they ought, judge righteous judgement, <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.24. neither M. <hi>Ley</hi> nor C. <hi>D.</hi> will have any cauſe to be afraid of their definitive ſentence, in the triall before them.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I intend not to puzzle the world with any more of this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is one of the wiſeſt, and honeſteſt paſſages in your An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, if you be true to what you tell your <hi>Reader;</hi> for it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieth <hi>a confeſſion</hi> (of that which you injuriouſly object to M. <hi>Ley</hi> in the beginning of your Letter) of puzling the world, your Readers, your ſimple Readers, you ſhould ſay, for neither the world, nor the wiſe in it will be puzled with ſuch poore trifles as you preſent, and ſend abroad; and <hi>a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> that you will offend in that kinde no more; wiſe and good men will be glad to take you at your word: but I doubt you will not be ſo good a man, as to make them believe you will take up a controverſie, unleſſe you may have the laſt word.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:113626:23"/>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Some truth may be ſeene, and what is more is but you and I.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>More truth might have beene ſeene, if you had uſed ſuch plaine dealing as your duty required. What you meane by <hi>What is more is but you and I,</hi> I doe not clearly underſtand; whether what is more then truth, or then that truth which is already ſeene, <hi>is but you and I,</hi> that is, our adverſe aſſertions, yet there is a truth in them on one ſide, or other; but for this, <hi>Si non vis intelligi debes negligi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, I was unwilling to ſet your failings before you, and the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It ſeemes ſo in fact, becauſe you have ſet none but your owne faylings of truth and honeſty before the world; but ſure your affection was to make others believe you have made ſuch diſcoveries of him as might diſgrace him. But are you ſo blinded with ſelfe-love, as to believe that any wiſe Reader of M. <hi>Leys</hi> writings and yours will thinke you meant to have any mercy on his reputation, if he had juſtly incurred the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of your penne?</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But ſince you printed them once over in miſtake, I thought I might print them over in a clearer letter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not ſo cleare, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, but that there is more <hi>Smoke</hi> then <hi>Light</hi> in the words you uſe. For what meane you by M. <hi>Ley his printing of his faylings by miſtake?</hi> you meane ſure to be miſtak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, elſe you would not wrap up your meaning in ſuch intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate expreſſions; and when your minde is knowne, it will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve into the miſtake of your laſt words in your 11. <hi>pag.</hi> as they follow.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That you may ſee things for errours, which before you tooke for truths.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You muſt be a <hi>Thaumaturgus,</hi> M. <hi>S.</hi> and change the nature
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:113626:24"/>of things, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did when he turned a rod into a ſerpent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you can make either M. <hi>Ley,</hi> or any judicious man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that errour is his, and truth yours in the controverſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt you. But that you ſhould conceive that ſuch a little broken, darke and dulky glaſſe ſhould make him ſee any ſuch change as you talke of, is ſuch a fiction in your owne fancy as will never thrive to a fallacy in any other that is not wholly yours already.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>Concluſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus I have replyed to your poſitions, not to your paſſions, nor reproaches, wherein you are ſomething larger then I had thought becomes an orthodox Divine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Your <hi>Concluſion,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, is but <hi>Colluſion,</hi> wherein you have many wayes uncharitably abuſed M. <hi>Ley.</hi> and fallaciouſly endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make your Readers miſdeem the difference betwixt him and you, as if by ſuch ſmall ſnipps, and ſnatches at M. <hi>Leys laſt large Book</hi> (as you call it) you had given a good and juſt account of it to competent Iudges. You would make them believe that M. <hi>Ley</hi> was impotently paſſionate, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull in his paſſions, and that your ſelf were a man of a better mould and temper then <hi>Elias</hi> was, <hi>Iames.</hi> 5.17. made up meerly of Evangelicall mildnes: <hi>when</hi> indeed M. <hi>Ley</hi> hath been ſo paſſive under you, and patient towards you, as hath put him to make his Apology to ſome of no meane place, for ſuch an immoderate moderation, as is at further diſtance from juſt ſeverity, then from partial indulgence. And if any of his language ſeem harſh unto you, it is but the correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of his character to your carriage, he doth but make his expreſſion according to the print of your provocations.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For the dire you caſt in my face, I have onely wiped it off, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out caſting it back on yours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>M. <hi>Ley</hi> hath caſt no dirt upon your face, but onely ſet a looking-glaſſe and <hi>Light</hi> before your eyes, that you might ſee
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:113626:24"/>your ſpots and waſh your face. And for that <hi>wining off the dare</hi> you ſpeake of, it is but like the adultereſſes wiping of her mouth (ſaying, ſhe hath done no wickednes, <hi>Pro.</hi> 30.20.) which was the more foule, by ſuch an hypocritical clearing of her ſelfe; and ſuch is yours in this place.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For your revilings, ſlightings, and raylings, if they trouble not your ſelfe to write, the Preſſe to Print, the Reader to read, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe you they trouble not me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>ſlighting</hi> of your papers you cannot juſtly blame M. <hi>Ley,</hi> ſince there is ſo litle in them to inſtruct, or edifie a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that I doubt not but every prudent and impartiall man, that hath had the patience to peruſe them, and to compare them with M. <hi>Leys</hi> Books, hath taken his leave of them with extreme diſlike for their ſlightnes and emptities; as a man would doe at the offer of chaff for wheat, leaves for fruit, <hi>Smoke</hi> for <hi>Light;</hi> nay you your ſelfe have ſlighted them, in a ſudden and extemporary obtruſion of them to the Preſſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out due conſideration of them before they came thither, or conſiderate review of their errata when they came thence.</p>
               <p>But for <hi>revilings</hi> and <hi>raylings,</hi> you cannot object them to him without reviling and railing, and I dare challenge you, on his behalfe, to ſhew any expreſſions of his, which you take to come under ſo contumelious a Title, and I will make proof that there is warrant for them in your owne words; and that there is not one letter of aggravation in them above the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of your guilt; and therefore, S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, they ſhould <hi>Trouble</hi> you, and humble you, becauſe you have deſerved them, and not M. <hi>Ley,</hi> whoſe words, if they be taken at the worſt, are but meet and even with your merit.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And though I am much below many, yet I am in this above you, that I can forgive you, by how much he that can pardon is greater them he that offends.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Who they be, and how many, or few they be whom you
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:113626:25"/>acknowledge your ſelf to be below I cannot tell; but in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming ſuch a lamb-like lenity, as without any trouble to take notice of ſuch, and ſo great injury as you complain of, and yet to be ſo ready to pardon, as you pretend, and (as you brag in the next paragraph) to thank your adverſary for his ill uſage of you, is to climbe much higher in ſelf-exaltation then M. <hi>Ley</hi> had done, if he had ſaid ten times more in his own commendation of that kinde which you objected to him. For it is the higheſt degree of Evangelicall grace, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Angelicall cloquence, Propheticall intelligence, miraculous confidence <hi>(even to removing of mountains)</hi> above moſt profuſe benificence, giving all a mans goods to feed the poor, above the patience of martyrdom, of willing martyrdom, under the hotteſt torments, <hi>giving the body to be burned,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſets it out, in the thirteenth chapter of his former Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And whereas, out of your ſuperabundant grace, you ſay, you can pardon him, why do you not do it? why did you not forbear further to abuſe him in this laſt paper of yours? that ſo, according to the ambition of your minde, you might be above him in benevolence. But if you had made none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther returne to his laſt book, then your <hi>Diploma</hi> of <hi>indulgence</hi> unto him, and pardon of him, under your hand and ſeal, he might have ſcorned to accept it, as a <hi>Bull</hi> or a pardon from the <hi>Pope, ſub annulo piſcatoris;</hi> ſince, though you were ſuch a pardoner as<note n="*" place="margin">Is (ſcic <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celius</hi>) inter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia docebat, ſe tantam habere poteſtatem a pontifice, ut e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiamſi quis vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginem matrem vitiaſſet ac gravidam ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſet, condona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re crimen ipſe poſſet, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventu pecuniae: deinde, non mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ddjam commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa, verumeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ſutura pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata condona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat. <hi>Sleidan Comment.</hi> l. <hi>13.</hi> fol. <hi>209.</hi> pag b.</note> 
                  <hi>Tecelius</hi> boaſted himſelf to be, he is no of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender againſt you, to put you to the practice of patience towards him, or him to the purchaſe of a pardon from you.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I thank you for your ill uſage, you cannot do that againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> which works not for my good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What are your rebukes, when your thanks are ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches? wherein you magnify your ſelf, and vilify your adverſary as much as may be. And if you think as you ſay, he cannot do that againſt you which works not for your
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113626:25"/>good, I hope it will do you good, and it's my deſire to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover your hypocriſy, by ſetting your profeſſion and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in a poſture fit for a mutuall and reciprocall aſpect from the one to the other.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For I am learning to bleſſe thoſe that curſe me, to pray for thoſe that deſpightfully uſe me?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You are learning? with ſuch profciency in charity, as the ſilly women made in knowledge, of whom <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>that they were ever learning, and never came to the knowledge of the truth,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.7.</p>
               <p>J. S.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Learning to bleſſe:</hi> To bleſſe in that ſenſe wherein <hi>Jobs</hi> wife ſpake to her husband, <hi>Iob.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Bleſſe God and die,</hi> for ſo the word <hi>Barech</hi> in the primary ſignification of the originall muſt be rendred, though ſometimes by a figure, called <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemia,</hi> it be put for curſing, as in that place.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And to pray for them that deſpightfully uſe me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Charity is the chief of evangelicall graces, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.1. and you pretend to the higheſt degree of it, the returning of bleſſing for curſing, prayers for reproaches, and deſpightfull uſages, to be a friend to your enemies, when you play the enemy with your friend. Such an one you had juſt cauſe to accompt M. <hi>Ley,</hi> who firſt appeared in profeſſion, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of reſpect unto you, before you ſhewed your ſelf any way well affected to him: and (excepting his engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the truth, which did as much oblige him to be an adverſary, as Chriſtianity did to be no enemy) he was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to continue an ingenuous correſpondence with you even to the laſt; and therefore in a friendly manner he ſent you his laſt book, as well as his firſt that he wrote againſt you: But you, for all your fair ſhews of Evangelicall lenity and love, have been very bitter, and ſplenative towards him, endeavouring to render him to the Reader an indiſcreet and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:113626:26"/>vain boaſter, a ſhifting tergiverſator, a ſlanderer, a rayler, a reviler, and perſecutour, and many times you have with an Iſhmaelitiſh jeer, like a venemous pill wrapt up in leaf-gold, endeavoured to taint, and poyſon his reputation, ſo farre as your credit would reach, to the ruine of it.</p>
               <p>It is true (and obvious to the obſervation of any intelligent man, that marks the temper and complection of your Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius) that you affect ſuch expreſſions of your rancor and reproach, as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> noteth of an hypocriticall malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: <hi>The words of his mouth are ſmoother then butter, but war was is his heart; his words were ſofter then oyl, yet were they drawen ſwords,</hi> Pſal. 55.21. and like a dog<note n="*" place="margin">Purch Pilgr. of Relig.</note> of <hi>Congo,</hi> to bite, though you bark not.</p>
               <p>J. S. <hi>pag.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And truly this advantage I ſhall make of your taxing me for faults which I have not, to tax my ſelf for many other faults which I have indeed, which you and the world ſees not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You have not, nor can you truly object any charge un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truly impoſed upon you by Maſter <hi>Ley.</hi> And for taxing your ſelf for faults, which Maſter <hi>L.</hi> and the world ſee not, you will ſee ere long perhaps that M. <hi>Ley</hi> hath been chary of your credit, when you ſhall read in black and white from another hand, that which may make you pale with guilt, or red with ſhame; whereof there may be pregnant proof, though neither he, nor the world were eye witneſſes of your faults; and which he was not willing to upbraid you with, though he were confidently informed of it, and ſeriouſly ſollicited to make it a part of his recrimination againſt you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:113626:26"/>
               <head>A <hi>Review</hi> of the Teſtimony of <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſius,</hi> cited by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Saltm.</hi> the ſecond time, with much ignorance, or little conſcience, touching the form of <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> and the Right of <hi>Preſbytery.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>J. S.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR</hi> Salmaſius <hi>his Testimony, with the Baptiſme in the Name of the Lord? Jeſus Chriſt: and his teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony that the Preſbytery is but of humane, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive right, not of divine; He is mine, and not yours: and all your pains, and quarelling, and after-quotations cannot make him more yours, or leſſe mine; and it is no little diſadvantage to you, that one ſo great a Scholar at your whole Aſſembly affords my, hath thus witneſſed with the truth, which ſo many Scholars oppoſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L. M.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was too much unfaithfulnes, eſpecially in ſuch a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall penman as you would be reputed, that you did once en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to delude your <hi>Reader</hi> with a miſallegation of the Learned <hi>Salmaſius;</hi> but now again (after you have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected in your ill dealing) and there are as many witneſſes of your falſehood therein, as there have been indifferent Readers of the writings betwixt M. <hi>L.</hi> and you) to reſume the ſame Teſtimony, and not only to miſapply it to the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage of your erroneous opinions, but to call an ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and clear confutation of you, <hi>quarrelling,</hi> and to glory that <hi>Salmaſius</hi> is ſo much yours, that it is no little diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to our ſide, that one ſo great a Scholar as the Aſſembly affords any, hath ſo witneſſed with the truth in your ſence, and this upon your bare affirmation, without ſo much as a
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:113626:27"/>pretence of proof, as if your word were an oracle in your own cauſe, all theſe ill qualified ingredients, made up into an entire Dos, amount to ſuch an exceſſe of immodeſty, as without an overcourteous charlentiſmus cannot properly be called by any term or title on this ſide <hi>impudence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Howſoever, your evil dealing (by an overruling provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which produceth good out of evil) may bring forth this good effect; <hi>viz.</hi> That the truth may be further cleared, and you more abundantly convinced, and conſequently the more aſhamed of your confident boaſting of your partly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and partly feigned atteſtation of <hi>Salmaſius</hi> for your Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, in point of Baptiſme and Independencie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Of Baptiſme.</p>
               <p>Whereof you mention two particulars, the one of the matter of it, the other of the forme. For the matter of it, as you bring it to, it is river water, and of that for matter of fact, there is no doubt but that the firſt Baptiſme in the New Teſtament was in river water, and at the river <hi>Jordan, Matth.</hi> 3.6. afterwards ſome were Baptized in<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieron.</hi> de locis Hebr.</note> fountains, as the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> Act. 8.38. Some in rivers, as <hi>Lydia,</hi> Act. 16.15. Some in particular houſes, as the <hi>Gaiter</hi> in the priſon, <hi>ver.</hi> 33. of the ſame chapter.</p>
               <p>And for matter of right, no orthodox Divine hath held any of them unlawfull.</p>
               <p>But for the form of Baptiſme, there is much queſtion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that; which, if M. <hi>Saltmarſh</hi> had ſaid nothing at all, may deſerve a diligent diſcuſſion. But I ſhall do ſomewhat the more in it, for the diſcovery of his either ignorance, or inconſideration in the cauſe, For the clearing whereof we are to obſerve, that the Sacrament of Baptiſme hath been di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly adminiſtred by acts,
<list>
                     <item>1. Preparative, and</item>
                     <item>2. Executive.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, For <hi>preparation,</hi> ſuch as were new converts to true Religion, and were competently endowed with qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons intellectuall and morall, prepared themſelves, by<note n="a" place="margin">Ingreſſures Baptiſmum o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retronibus cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris, jejunijs &amp; geniculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onibus, &amp; por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigilsij orare portet, &amp; cum confeſſione omnium retrò delictorum. <hi>Tertul</hi> de Baptiſm.</note> 
                  <hi>fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent prayers, faſtings, kneelings, watchings, with confeſſion of their former ſins.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:113626:27"/>
               <p>Secondly, For acts <hi>excentive</hi> for the performance of the Sacrament, the manner hath been<note n="*" place="margin">Pro diverſo fidelium ſtatu potuit ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum Initi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ationis varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, <hi>Gerard. Job. Voſſij,</hi> Theſ. <hi>30.</hi> pag. <hi>405.</hi>
                  </note> various in the ſeverall ages of the Church; As when <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptized, there was a confeſſion of ſins made by thoſe who were of years, when they were made partakers of the Sacrament; And no doubt, though it be not expreſſed ſet down, they made <hi>profeſſion of their faith alſo,</hi> becauſe it is ſaid by our Saviour, <hi>He that beleeveth and is baptized ſhall be ſaved, but he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeveth not ſhall be damned,</hi> Mark. 16.16. <hi>and of their repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance alſo,</hi> becauſe <hi>Iohns</hi> Baptiſme was called <hi>the Baptiſme of repentance,</hi> Mark 1.4. Act. 13.24. &amp; chap. 19. ver. 4. And the Baptiſme of the Apoſtles was therein agreeable to the Baptiſme of <hi>John:</hi> For thoſe they baptized <hi>were bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed into Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 6.3. which could not be without ſaith, nor could the faith be known but by profeſſion; and repentance was required to be profeſſed as well as faith in their Apoſtolicall adminiſtration of Baptiſme, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Peter</hi> joyns them both together, <hi>Repent and be Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed,</hi> Act. 2.38.</p>
               <p>Afterwards to theſe particulars ſome others were added, <hi>as the renunciation of the Devil, with his pomps and Angels,</hi> mentioned by divers<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Origen.</hi> Hom. <hi>12.</hi> in Num. <hi>Baſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> lib. de spit. ſonct. c. <hi>11. Chryſoſt.</hi> Hom. <hi>21.</hi> ad pop. Antlech.</note> Greek, and<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tertul.</hi> de Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>. c. <hi>1. Cyprian.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Ambroſ.</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> de Sacramentis c. <hi>2.</hi> &amp; l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>7. Hieron.</hi> in c. <hi>6.</hi> Amos. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> de ſymb. ad Catechumenos c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> Latine Fathers, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in<note n="d" place="bottom">Concil, Eariſ. cap. <hi>10.</hi> Tom. <hi>6.</hi> Concil. p. <hi>326.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Concilic Pariſienſi,</hi> which were reduced to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatoties, as in the Baptiſme of the Eunuch by <hi>Philip, Act.</hi> 8. which<note n="e" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Grot.</hi> Annot. in Matth. <hi>28.19.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Grotins</hi> turns into an interrogatory thus: <hi>Doest thou beleave with all thine beart?</hi> But the words are, <hi>if thou believeſt with all thine heart, thou mayest</hi> be Baptized, <hi>and he anſwered and ſaid, I believe that Joſue Chriſt is the Son of God,</hi> ver. 37.</p>
               <p>Which, though it ſuited well with thoſe times, (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſuch as were of full age, were able to anſwer for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) was very impertinently, if not abſurdly applied to the Baptiſme of children, both in the Popiſh Miſſall, and in the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:113626:28"/>Engliſh Service book, either to the childe, or to them that preſented it to Baptiſme, as in the childes name and ſtead; for ſo it was meant, as is manifeſt by the laſt Queſtion, <hi>wilt thou be Baptized in this faith?</hi> Though to thoſe that brought the childe to be Baptized ſuch a queſtion might be put, as we finde it in the form of adminiſtration of Baptiſme in the Church of <hi>Geneva,</hi> ſet out in <hi>Calvins Opuſcula,</hi> where alſo we ſinde the recitall of the <hi>Creed,</hi> the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> end the <hi>Impoſition of a name</hi> on the Baptized, whereof we finde no footſteps in the Apoſtles time, though<note n="f" place="margin">Martinus Cantapetren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, 5. <hi>lypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>typ. c.</hi> 1.</note> ſome conceive (but cannot prove out of Scripture) that <hi>Sauls</hi> name at his Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme was changed into the name <hi>Paul;</hi> much leſſe can the Papiſts prove their manifold additions, which reckoned all together, make up the number of 22. ceremonies,<note n="g" place="margin">Bel. <hi>de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. Bapt. l.</hi> 1 <hi>c</hi> 25 <hi>Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>p</hi> 368.</note> twelve before Baptiſme,<note n="h" place="margin">Ibid. <hi>c.</hi> 26.</note> five with it,<note n="i" place="margin">Ibid <hi>c.</hi> 27.</note> and five after it.</p>
               <p>But that which moſt concerns our preſent inquirie is, <hi>The form of words</hi> wherewith it is principally to be adminiſtred, whereof<note n="k" place="margin">Accedat ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum ad elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, &amp; fit Sacramentum. <hi>Aug. Tract. in Johan. 80.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Let the word be added to the element, and they two make up the Sacrament.</hi> Where we will not take up the Queſtion betwixt Proteſtants and Papiſts, concerning the<note n="l" place="margin">Chamier <hi>de Sacrament is in Genere l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 15. <hi>Tom.</hi> 4. <hi>Ponſtrat p.</hi> 32. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>conſecratory</hi> and <hi>concionatory</hi> word, for we may reſolve in brief, that the ſame form of words, though they be <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cionatory,</hi> as containing publike inſtruction to thoſe that are preſent at the Sacrament, (and if they be not ſo, they are no meet words for that ſacred ſervice) may be <hi>conſecratory</hi> to the Inſtitution, and Adminiſtration of the Sacrament; and that's the ſpeciall uſe for which they are to be rehearſed. Taking the words in this ſence, we may divide the whole Queſtion into theſe particular Queries.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Whether there be any form of words for the adminiſtration of Baptiſme at all?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>If ſo, Whether there have been one certain and conſtant form obſerved in the Scripture, and what difference of forms may be collected out of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Among divers forms; which is the chief?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Whether any one be ſo neceſſary that it is not lawfull to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from it?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:113626:28"/>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>If any variation be lawfull, What may be admitted without marring the Sacrament, what not?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1 Querie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether there be any for me of winds for adminiſtration of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme at all?</hi> This queſtion is occaſioned by<note n="m" place="margin">Bellarm <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Bapt. c.</hi> 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> who, following <hi>Durand</hi> the ſchooleman, holds that <hi>Iohn</hi> bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed without any for me of words. But 1<note n="n" place="margin">Barth. Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na <hi>in tertiam partem Th. q.</hi> 38 <hi>art. o. p.</hi> 803.</note> 
                  <hi>Barth, Medina,</hi> another ſchoolman of great note, for he was Doctour of the Chaire in the Univerſitie of <hi>Salmanen,</hi> holds the contrary. And ſecondly as a learned<note n="o" place="margin">Gerard, <hi>Loc. Com Tom.</hi> 4. <hi>p</hi> 450. <hi>num.</hi> 46.</note> Lutheran Anſwereth, <hi>To admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter the Sacrament without any for me of words, were to make the Sacrament a dumbe ſhew.</hi> Thirdly, whereas <hi>Bellarm:</hi> pretends for a reaſon of his opinion, that if <hi>Iohn</hi> uſed any form; it was <hi>In the Name of the Mesſias to come,</hi> and that he uſed the ſame forme to all alike (to Chriſt as well as to others) whom he baptiſed,<note n="p" place="margin">Etiam Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum baptiza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit Iohannes coritu quo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teros, &amp; certe ridiculum ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſet Chriſtum baptizaſſe in nomine ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri. <hi>Bellarm.</hi> ubt ſupra p. <hi>352.</hi>
                  </note> But it <hi>would be ridiculous to ſay</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that he baptiſed Chriſt in the Name of him that was to come.</hi> To this it may be replyed, and the Reply will be proved in the reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the next Doubt, That <hi>Iohn</hi> did <hi>not</hi> uſe one forme unto all, (that is, to Chriſt and to all the Chriſtians he baptiſed) <hi>For it had been rather ridiculous to have made no difference in words, where there was ſo great difference in perſons,</hi> and times, then to varie with reſpect unto them, as we ſhall ſeaſonably obſerve in the clearing of the next enſuing Quere.</p>
               <p>2 Querie.</p>
               <p>The Second Querie is. <hi>Whether we find one certain, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant forme of Baptiſme, either preſcribed or obſerved in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and what difference of forms may be collected out of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall draw down the reſolution of his doubt by certaine graduall propoſitions.</p>
               <p>Firſt, It is certain that <hi>Iohn</hi> did not baptize in his owne name, no more then <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Cor. 1. <hi>Were yee baptized,</hi> ſayd he, <hi>in the name of Paul,</hi> v. 13. <hi>I thanke God that I baptized none of you but Criſpus and Gajus, leſt any ſhould ſay that I baptized in mine own Name,</hi> ver. 14, 15. for he bare witneſſe of Chriſt, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.7. as comming after him, yet indeed preferred before him, ver. 15. and though as <hi>the Sun of man</hi> a little after him, as
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:113626:29"/>
                  <hi>the Son of God</hi> ſo far before him, as to be ſtiled <hi>the ever laſting Father,</hi> Eſay 9.6. and ſo farr above him, as that he profeſſed, when he baptized him, he was <hi>not worthy to unlooſe the latchet of his ſhoe,</hi> ver. 27. <hi>and he confeſſed and denied not, but confeſſed, I am not that Chriſt,</hi> ver. 20. And being <hi>uſked, What then? art thou Elias? he ſayd, I am not; Art thou that prophet? and he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, No,</hi> ver. 12. and being further demanded, <hi>Who art thou, what ſayeſt thou of thy ſelfe?</hi> ver. 22. <hi>he ſayd, I am the voyce of one crying in the wildernes, Make ſtraight the way of the Lord, as ſaid the prophet Eſaias.</hi> ver 23.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Not baptizing in his own Name, theſe Texts doe intimate that he baptized in his Name, who was ſo far above him, and whoſe forerunner he was, to prepare the way for him. And it is manifeſt that he baptized <hi>In the Name of the Lord Ieſus,</hi> Acts. 19.6. for thoſe words are to be referred to <hi>Johns</hi> baptiſme, which is repeated in the ſtory of <hi>Luke,</hi> not to any rebaptization of the diſciples by the Apoſtle, who before were baptized with the Baptiſme of <hi>John,</hi> as the<note n="q" place="margin">Bellarm. <hi>de Sacr. Bapt. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 22. <hi>Tom.</hi> 3 <hi>p</hi> 359. Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranus <hi>in Act.</hi> 19 <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 506. <hi>Eſtius in lib. Sent.</hi> 4. <hi>diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inct.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 38.</note> Papiſts contend, that they may prove a great difference betwixt the baptiſme of <hi>Iohn,</hi> and the baptiſme of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles. And I am ſorry to read the like expoſition for rebaptization in the Annotations of ſo orthodox a Divine as <hi>Deodat;</hi> for <hi>Iohns</hi> Baptiſme was a true, and ſufficient Baptiſme, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there was no need of a rebaptizing of thoſe whom he baptized before; nor were they baptized again, but hands im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on them, and their baptiſme thereby approved. For though the ſupper of the Lord be adminiſtred often, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>ver.</hi> 25.26. becauſe we have need to be often <hi>ſpiritually,</hi> as wel as <hi>corporally</hi> fed; yet Baptiſme, which is the meanes of our ingraffing into Chriſt, of our admiſſion and entolment into the Church of Chriſt, and of our now birth, is done but once, as we are born but once.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The mention of Chriſt by <hi>Iohn</hi> was not only ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wiſe, as<note n="r" place="margin">Tantum adma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muiſse populum, ut crederent in venturum Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiam. <hi>Bell.</hi> l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. de Bap. c. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> would have it, who ſayth <hi>that Iohn did only admoniſh the people to believe in Chriſt who was to come;</hi> But he uſed ſome words of Chriſt in the adminiſtration of Baptiſme Sacramentally, as all orthodox Divines doe unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly agree.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:113626:29"/>
               <p>Fourthly, For the words uſed by <hi>Iohn</hi> at his Baptiſme, though we cannot be certain of them, becauſe we finde no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe ſcripture for them, as<note n="ſ" place="margin">Voſſ. Theſ. <hi>de Bapt.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 393.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſſeus</hi> warily aſſerteth, yet it is very probable that they were<note n="t" place="margin">Veſſ. Theſ. 30. <hi>p.</hi> 405.</note> varyed, according to the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent condition of perſons whom he baptized, and of the time wherein, &amp; the ſtate of him in whoſe <hi>Name</hi> he baptized.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Before Chriſt was manifeſted the Meſſias who was expected, (which was illuſt riouſly ſet forth at his baptiſme in the river Iordan,) <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptized in his Name as yet to come, as may be collected out of <hi>Act.</hi> 19.4. Hence divers, both of the ancient Fathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, and of the Schoolmen, have concluded that <hi>John</hi> baptized in this form,<note n="a" place="margin">Baptizo te in nomine venturi Meſſiae; ſic <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cron</hi> in <hi>Ioel</hi> chap. <hi>2. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſ</hi> l <hi>1</hi> de S. S. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp; in epiſt, de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xorts v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ro. <hi>Alexander.</hi> Alenſis <hi>4.</hi> part. queſt. <hi>9.</hi> monit. <hi>2. Lumbard.</hi> ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ent l. <hi>4.</hi> diſt. <hi>2.</hi> pag <hi>697. Aquinas in 4.</hi> lib. ſent. diſt. <hi>2. Barth.</hi> de <hi>Medina</hi> in <hi>3.</hi> part. <hi>Thom</hi> q <hi>38</hi> art. <hi>6.</hi> p. <hi>801.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>I baptize thee in the Name of him who was, or is to come;</hi> and with them agreeth<note n="b" place="bottom">Voſ. <hi>ubi ſupra, p.</hi> 393.</note> 
                  <hi>Gerard. Ioh. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oſſius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, When he was come, and gloriouſly manifeſted by a viſible ſigne, and glorious acknowledgment from heaven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. then he did not ſay, as before, <hi>I baptize thee in the name of him that was, or is to come, but in the Name of him who is come, and hath been among you, in the midſt of you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, When he baptized our Saviour Chriſt, it was not like that he would uſe ſuch words to him, as he uſed to others; For to others Baptiſme was a waſhing away of ſin, and he had none, and therefore Baptiſme was not neceſſary to him; for, as<note n="c" place="margin">Baptizari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis Domine Ieſu? quid tibl opus ſuct bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumate? nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid ſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> eſt medicina, ac mundatione mundo? unde tihi peccatum ut baptiſma ſit neceſſari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>? nanqui la patre? patren quidem babes, ſed De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, &amp; ae qualis es illi, Deus de Deo, Lunen de Lumine; Nam in Deum peccarum cadere non paſſe qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> neſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>? an verb le matre? nam &amp; matrem babes, ſed oirgo eſt — Quam maculan poteſt babere agum ſine maculd? — Iohannes baptizavit aguum &amp; aquas Idvit. <hi>Bern.</hi> ſermon. <hi>1.</hi> in epiphan. Dom. col. <hi>76.</hi> B. C.</note> 
                  <hi>Bernard</hi> hath it in his patheticall Apoſtrophe to Chriſt, <hi>Lord Ieſus wilt thou be baptized? why, what need haſt thou of Baptiſme I doth the ſound ſtand in need of a phyſitian, or the cleans of waſhing? whence hadſt thou any ſinnne thai ſhould be waſhed away by baptiſme? hadſt thou any ſinne from thy Father? why he was God, and thou art equall to him, God of God, Light of Light, and who knowes not that in God there can be no ſin? or hadſt thou ſin from thy mother? amother indeed thou hadſt, but ſhe was a virgin.</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:113626:30"/>He ſhould have added, and though not altogether with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin, her ſeed was ſanctified by the holy Ghoſt at his concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; He goeth on, <hi>What ſtaine could be found in him who was a lambe without ſpot? Iohn baptized the lambe</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>and by that baptiſme waſht the waters.</hi> He was baptized then not as guilty of ſin, and ſo not as needing baptiſmall regeneration, but <hi>to fulfill all righteouſnes.</hi> Math. 3.15. to ſubmit himſelfe as under the law, comming in the forme of a ſervant, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.7. though he were the Law-maker; and therefore he was cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, as well as baptized, to honour his owne Ordinance with his owne example, and to be conformable to man in all things, ſin only excepted.</p>
               <p>Nor was it fit to baptize him <hi>in the Name of him that was to come;</hi> How then, or with what forme of words was he bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized? I haue met with no Authour but one, who takes upon him affirmatively and diſtinctly to anſwer that queſtion; and it is<note n="d" place="margin">Palacius 2. <hi>de Bapt. c.</hi> 33.</note> 
                  <hi>Palacius</hi> a Papiſt who ſayth, he baptized him thus, <hi>I baptize thee in thine owne name, who waſt to come.</hi> Wherein, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo punctuall in his reſolution, he was too preſumptuous. Yet on the other hand, they are as far out who ſay, as<note n="e" place="margin">Marſilius <hi>&amp;</hi> Paludanus <hi>apud</hi> Lorin. <hi>in</hi> Act. <hi>c.</hi> 19. <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 705. <hi>col.</hi> 2. Bellarm <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Bapt. c.</hi> 20. <hi>Tom</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 35<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſome doe, that <hi>Iohn</hi> uſed no form of words at all in the Baptiſme of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Fourthly,<note n="f" place="margin">Magdeburg. <hi>Centur.</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. Chamier. <hi>Tom.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 13. <hi>p</hi> 277.</note> Some learned Divines hold that <hi>Iohn</hi> did, at leaſt ſometimes, baptize <hi>in the Name of the Father, Son and Holy ghoſt;</hi> although ſome<note n="g" place="margin">Bellarm. <hi>l</hi> 1. <hi>de ſacra. Bapt. c.</hi> 23.</note> Papiſts do with ſuch confidence deny it,<note n="h" place="margin">Lorin. <hi>in Act Apoſt. c.</hi> 10. <hi>v. a. p.</hi> 704. <hi>col.</hi> 2.</note> as to hold it impudence to affirm it. And they hold ſo the rather, to maintain their Tenet againſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, of the eſſentiall difference of the Baptiſme of <hi>John,</hi> from the Baptiſme inſtituted by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> according to his command, and commiſſion given to the Apoſtles, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19.</p>
               <p>But it is probable enough that he did in his Baptiſme make mention of the Trinity; becauſe,</p>
               <p n="1">1. He had the ſame warrant of divine authority for what he did, which the Apoſtles had, <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.33.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe<note n="i" place="margin">Sic argument. <hi>Chamterus</hi> lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce citato.</note> he was an orthodox Divine, and acquainted with the Doctrine of the Trinity.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:113626:30"/>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe at the baptiſme of our Saviour there was a moſt cleare manifeſtation of the Trinity, the father acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging his Sonne from heaven, and the holy ghoſt lighting on him in the likenes of a Dove. And therefore it is like he made mention of the Trinity, (at leaſt after Chriſts Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me at Iordan) by way of ſupplication, or of ſacramentall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, though ordinarily he baptized <hi>In the Name of Chriſt Ieſus, or of the Meſſias which was to come.</hi> But whether he uſed the one, or the other form before the act, or inſtantly with the act of Baptizing (as our manner is at this day) is very uncertain.</p>
               <p>The third Querie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of the ſeverall Formes</hi> of Baptiſme <hi>which is the chief?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The cheif forme for authority, and perpetuity, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity is that whereof <hi>Math.</hi> 28.19. is the ground, <hi>I bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize thee in the Name of the Father, Sonne, and Holy ghoſt.</hi> And though it be not neceſſary to conceive that miniſters are bound formally, expreſſaly, and preciſely to apply theſe words to the act of baptizing, yet ſince no ſence is aſſigned to them when they are ſo applied, but what is very congruous to the act of the Miniſter, it cannot but be a very ſafe way explicit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to mention them in the baptiſmal action. For whether we meane by <hi>I baptize thee in the Name of the Father, Sonne, and Holy ghoſt,</hi> I baptize thee by the power, authority, or commiſſion from God (as <hi>Acts.</hi> 3.6. and <hi>Acts.</hi> 4.7.) who is owne in ſubſtance, three in perſons, Father Sonn, and Holy ghoſt; or whether by thoſe words we imply a prayer for the bleſſing of the Trinity upon the baptized perſon, or engage him to the profeſſion of the fayth, and worſhip of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Trinity, or what other orthodox ſence we aſſigne unto the words, they may well be taken in that ſence, when ſprinkling water upon the party baptized, or dipping him in the water, we ſay, <hi>I baptize thee in the Name of the Father. Sonne and Holy ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For this forme of Baptiſme there is very good warrant of ſcripture, reaſon, and practicall example. 1. For <hi>ſcripture,</hi> the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:113626:31"/>Text forecited out of <hi>Math,</hi> (as it is expounded) is plaine and pertinent, to which may be added the forecited illuſtrious teſtification of the Father to the Sonne, and the appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Holy Ghoſt in the forme of a dove, at our Saviours Baptiſme in the river Jordan. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For <hi>reaſon,</hi> we ſay that in baptiſme there is a concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent operation of grace, towards the party baptized, (who is within the Covenant)<note n="k" place="margin">Gerard. <hi>Loc. Com. Tom.</hi> 4. p. 488. ¶ 91.</note> whereby the Father receiveth him for a Sonne, the Sonne for a Brother, the Holy Ghoſt for a Temple.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For <hi>practicall example,</hi> we have firſt the Apoſtles, who received a Commiſſion from our Saviour to Baptize <hi>In the name of the Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt;</hi> which appeareth to have been the Apoſtolicall practize, by the paſſage betwixt <hi>Paul</hi> and the Diſciples found at <hi>Epheſus;</hi> for when <hi>Paul</hi> had put the queſtion to them, <hi>Whether they had received the Holy Ghoſt ſince they beleeved,</hi> and they had anſwered that <hi>they had not ſo much as heard whether there were an Holy Ghoſt or no,</hi> he replyed with a queſtion, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto what thou were yee baptized?</hi> as it were wondring, that they that were baptized, ſhould not have heard of the holy Ghoſt; which he had no cauſe to do, unleſſe there had been practicall example to baptize with mention of the Holy Ghoſt; And if the Holy Ghoſt were na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at Baptiſme, it is not probable that either the Father, or the Sonne were omitted.</p>
               <p>But whether the Apoſtles conſtantly kept to that forme is uncertain, Popiſh Authors confidently contradict each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this point; for<note place="margin">l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Petr. Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard. <hi>in Sent. l.</hi> 4. <hi>Diſtinct.</hi> 3 <hi>p.</hi> 699.</note> 
                  <hi>Peter Lombard</hi> reſolveth, that the Apoſtles baptized in the Name of the Trinity;<note place="margin">m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Eſtius <hi>in l.</hi> 4. <hi>Sent. diſt</hi> 3. ¶ 4. <hi>p.</hi> 40. <hi>col</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Eſtius</hi> aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that the Apoſtles alwayes baptized <hi>In the Name of the Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and he renders this reaſon, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, of one Sacrament there ſhould be but one forme, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially after a forme is preſcribed, as it was to the Apoſtles <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19.</p>
               <p>Others<note n="n" place="margin">Aur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>olus <hi>in</hi> 4. <hi>Sent. Diſt.</hi> 3. Franciſ Long. <hi>in Annot. in Can Apoſt.</hi> 40. <hi>p.</hi> 136. Harding. <hi>de Cor. ſabutra. queſpec art.</hi> 2.</note> ſay, that they had for a time a diſpenſation to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize <hi>In the name of Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> for ſpeciall honour to that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and Name, which was moſt expoſed to contempt.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:113626:31"/>But, if that had been a ſufficient reaſon why the Apoſtles ſhould baptize <hi>In the Name of Chriſt,</hi> and not <hi>of the Trinity,</hi> it is like our Saviour would have given his order of Baptiſme under that form.</p>
               <p>For the times after the Apoſtles, we finde many teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies for Baptiſme, <hi>In the name of the Father, Son and Holy Ghost,</hi> not only in the writings of ſuppoſitious, or ſuſpected Fathers, as<note n="o" place="margin">Clem. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. l</hi> 3 <hi>c.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp; l</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi> but in ſuch as are acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged for legitimate, as<note n="p" place="margin">Juſt, <hi>Mart. Apot.</hi> 2. <hi>ad</hi> Anton. <hi>Pium an</hi> 150.</note> 
                  <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> in his ſecond Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, and in the <hi>book of confeſſion, or expoſition of right faith,</hi> which goeth under his name, and if it be not his, as there is<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellar.</hi> de Eccleſ. Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torib p. <hi>64</hi> Scultet medul. patr. part. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> p. <hi>34.</hi>
                  </note> good reaſon at leaſt to doubt of it, yet is it very ancient, and that in the judgement both of<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> Proteſtant and Popiſh Authours;<note n="r" place="margin">Origen. <hi>in</hi> Rom 6. <hi>anno</hi> 226.</note> 
                  <hi>Origen,</hi>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">Greg. Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anz. <hi>Orat.</hi> 40. <hi>in Sanct. Bapt. an</hi> 370.</note> 
                  <hi>Greg. Nazianzen,</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="bottom">Epiphan <hi>haereſ.</hi> 62. <hi>Sabell. an</hi> 370.</note> 
                  <hi>Epiphanius,</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="bottom">Ambroſ. Mediolanenſ. <hi>de ſpir. Sanct. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>an.</hi> 374.</note> 
                  <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſ. Mediolanenſis,</hi>
                  <note n="w" place="bottom">Gaudent. Brixienſ. <hi>Tract. ſeu ſerm.</hi> 14. <hi>an.</hi> 390.</note> 
                  <hi>Gaudentius Brixienſis,</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="bottom">Auguſt. <hi>l.</hi> 13. <hi>contra</hi> Maxim <hi>c.</hi> 13. <hi>an.</hi> 420.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="bottom">Cyril. Alexand. <hi>lib de recta fide ad</hi> Theodoſ. <hi>Imperat. c.</hi> 32. <hi>an.</hi> 430.</note> 
                  <hi>Cyrillus Alexandrinus,</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="bottom">Gennad. Maſſil. <hi>lib. de Eccleſ Degmat. c.</hi> 52 <hi>an.</hi> 490.</note> 
                  <hi>Gennadius Maſſilienſis,</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Fulgent.</hi> lib con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra objectiones Arianorum in epileg. object. <hi>10.</hi> &amp; lib de Trinit. ad felicene Notar, c. <hi>2.</hi> an <hi>500.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Fulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="bottom">Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſius in cap. <hi>22.</hi> Apocalypſ. an. <hi>545.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Primaſius;</hi> All theſe were in the firſt five hundred years after Chriſt; In the ſixth Century was <hi>Gregory,</hi> ſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>the Great,</hi> of whom the ſaying is, he was <hi>the last of the good Biſhops of</hi> Rome, <hi>the firſt of the bad;</hi> and from him ſuch as were held moſt Orthodox in all age, both taught, and adminiſtred Baptiſme only <hi>In the name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After the Fathers, roſe up a race of Divines, called <hi>School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> of whom the firſt, and as it were the Father of the reſt, was<note n="c" place="margin">Petr. Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>ſent. diſt.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 701. <hi>an.</hi> 1145.</note> 
                  <hi>Peter Lombard,</hi> called <hi>the Maſter of the Sentences,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he collected the ſentences of the Divines of former a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and drew them into queſtions under ſeverall titles, in four books, whereof the firſt is of the Unity of God-head and Trinity of perſons; And in the fourth book, where be treats of the Sacraments, he affirmeth that the Apoſtles
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:113626:32"/>Baptized both before, and after the paſſion of our Saviour, <hi>In the name of the Father, Son, and Holy ghoſt;</hi> and according to him, in this particular, have the ſchoolmen that came after him reſolved for the conſtant uſ: of Baptiſme in that form, whereof to give in a Catalogue, with their teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, in a Chronologicall order for the times wherein they wrote, would be a long labour, and of little uſe; ſince (though univerſall conſent of all ſort of Authors make much for the honour, and eſtimation of any truth, yet) in this caſe it is needles, becauſe there is no learned Reader will doubt of it, and the ignorant will receive little ſatisfaction by a liſt of their names and Teſtimonies who are altogether unknowne unto them.</p>
               <p>If we draw neerer home for time, and place, and confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity in religion, we ſhall find the Doctrine and practiſe of the Reformed Churches concurring in this forme of Baptiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>In the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy ghoſt;</hi> which is a thing ſo well known by the <hi>Harmony,</hi> and <hi>Syntagma of Confeſſions,</hi> and by the obſervation of ſuch as have lived a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, that it were a ſuperfluous paynes to produce the proofe of them in particular.</p>
               <p>Unto plain and expreſſe Teſtimonies by words, we may adde a reall teſtimony by action, for baptizing <hi>In the name of the Trinity,</hi> which is the practice of Baptizing by trine-im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſion, or thrice dinning, and waſhing;<note n="d" place="margin">Petr. Lomb. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>Sent. Diſt.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 70<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>ex</hi> Greg. <hi>Ep.</hi> 41. Leandro <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſc.</hi>
                  </note> whereof two reaſons are rendred by <hi>Gregory,</hi> the one with ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant relation to the Trinity of perſons in the Unity of the Godhead; the other to the ſepulture of our Saviour for three dayes ſpace; but the principall is the former. And this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Baptizing is very ancient, for we find it the practice of the Church in<note n="e" place="margin">Dehinc ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergitamur. <hi>Tertul.</hi> de Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rona milit. c. <hi>5.</hi> Ter ad ſingula nomina in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonu ſingulu mergimur <hi>Idem adverſ. Praxeam c. 26.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Tortullians</hi> time; ſo ancient that divers of the<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ambroſ.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> de Sacram c. <hi>7. Hieron</hi> adverſ Luciſcrum. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> Serm. <hi>29.</hi> &amp; <hi>201.</hi> de Tempore.</note> Fathers take it for an Apoſtolicall tradition, and ſome have put it into an Apoſtolicall Canon to be obſerved upon a penalty, in theſe words.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Si quis epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copus aut Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter non tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam immerſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem unius my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterij celebret, ſed ſemel mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat in baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, (quod dari videtur in Domini morte) deponatur, &amp;c. <hi>Can. Apoſt. 50.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>If any Biſhop or Proſbyter do not celebrate the myſtery of Trine immerſion, or thrice dipping, but dippe but once in baptiſme (which ſeemes to be given in the death of the Lord) let him be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:113626:32"/>for the Lord ſaid not, Baptize ye in my death, but going teach all nation, baptizing them In the Name of the Father, Son, and holy ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But theſe Canons are not Canonicall; Orthodox Divines reject them as a parcell of Apocrypha, and the<note n="e" place="margin">Vid <hi>Petr.</hi> Sete Praeſat in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranz. Sum. Concil.</note> Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves admit of them but in part; and though if any ſhould baptize but once out of an hereticall miſapprehenſion of the bleſſed Trinity, ſuch a ſingle immerſion<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Theodoret.</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi> de haereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cor. fab.</note> might be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as it was in the <hi>Eunomians,</hi> who in oppoſition to the Doctrine of the Trinity dipped but once, yet there is no doubt but ſuch as baptize in a ſound ſence and judgement of the unity of the Godhead, and Trinity of perſons, though they do it but once, doe not amiſſe;<note n="g" place="margin">Petr. Lomb. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>ſent. diſt.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 702.</note> for both are lawfull, and as the Schoolmen determine, either of them may be uſed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the various cuſtome of orthodox Churches: and for this the fourth Councell of <hi>Toledo</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Concil. Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. <hi>4.</hi> in ſome Edit. Can. <hi>5.</hi> Tom. <hi>4.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. p. <hi>583.</hi> col. <hi>1.</hi> Edit. Bin. <hi>1636.</hi>
                  </note> made an expreſſe Canon, decreeing for a ſingle or ſimple dipping, againſt another ſort of hereticks, who by a trine immerſion profeſſed more then a perſonal diſtinction of the Father, Sonne, and holy ghoſt, as if they were of three diſtinct natures, not three diſtinct per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons onely; and by this decree they endeavoured to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way a ſcandalous difference of Baptiſme in <hi>Spain,</hi> while ſome baptized with a ſingle, and ſome with a three fold immerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or dipping; and by once dipping and thrice nameing of God by the Trinity of perſons, there was an Antidote pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided againſt both ſorts of hereſies,<note n="i" place="margin">Bonavent. in <hi>4.</hi> Seat. diſt. <hi>3.</hi> part. <hi>2.</hi> art. <hi>2.</hi> q. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> and the manner was this; At the firſt dipping <hi>the Father</hi> was named, at the ſecond <hi>the Sonne,</hi> at the third <hi>the holy ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fourth Querie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether any forme of baptiſme be ſo neceſſary that it is not lawfull to vary from it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The reſolution of this Querie is very various. For</p>
               <p n="1">1, Beſides that we have obſerved before out of <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> concerning <hi>Johns</hi> baptiſme without any forme of words, we are to obſerve,</p>
               <p n="1">1, That ſome hold there is no ſet forme of Baptiſmeſet downe in ſcripture which is neceſſary to be obſerved; This
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:113626:33"/>opinion<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bell.</hi> de Bapt l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> Tom. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>272.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmin</hi> imputeth to <hi>Luther, Zuinglius;</hi> and <hi>Bren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> as their errour.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the formes that are found in Scripture, that Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme <hi>In the Name of Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>of Chriſt Ieſus</hi> was lawfull, when <hi>John</hi> ſo baptized, for it is recorded in the Scripture, as before hath been ſhewed, and no where reproved; nor thoſe ſo baptized by him rebaptized, as hath been alſo ſhewed beofre.</p>
               <p n="3">3.<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bell</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> de Sacr. Bapt. c. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>276. Franciſe. Longus</hi> in Can. Apoſt. <hi>49.</hi> p. <hi>136.</hi>
                  </note> Some teach, that the Apoſtles baptized lawfully <hi>In the name of Chriſt,</hi> though without the addition of theſe words <hi>(which was to come)</hi> as well as <hi>In the name of the Trinity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. That it is lawfull for Miniſters ſo to baptize at this day, for the reaſon rendred by<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Baſil</hi> de ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. ſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Baſil,</hi> becauſe in one perſon all three are vertually included, as in the name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſigniſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>anointed,</hi> the perſon anointing, the father is imploied, and the perſon by whom he is anointed the holy Ghoſt. So, as<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Fred.</hi> Span. hem dab. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vang. part <hi>3.</hi> in <hi>Matth. 28.</hi> p. <hi>79.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Spanhemius</hi> ſaith, <hi>John</hi> Baptized In the Name of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity <hi>implicitly,</hi> though not <hi>explicitely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. For Baptiſme <hi>In the Name of the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt,</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Apul Suares loco ſub citato <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſome hold, that termes of equivalence, or equ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollence, bearing the ſame ſence, will ſerve for the forme of Baptiſme; as<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Clem. Conſtit. l. c. <hi>23.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>In the name of the ſending Father, or the Father that ſendeth. In the name of the Sonne that is come,</hi> and <hi>In the name of the witneſſing Comforter,</hi> or<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Suarez.</hi> in <hi>2.</hi> part Tham. Tom <hi>3.</hi> qui eſt primas de ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cram diſp <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> q <hi>66.</hi> ſell. <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>21<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>In the name of him that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth, of him that is begotten, and of the ſpirit proceding from them both.</hi> But the neerer the words come to thoſe of the 28. of <hi>Matth.</hi> 19. the more aſſuredly lawfull; as if one ſhould baptize <hi>In the name of the Father, the word, and the holy Ghoſt,</hi> 1 Iohn 5.7. Nor is that thought unlawfull to name each perſon with a word of explication added, as,<note n="h" place="margin">Egote hapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zo in no nine atris in geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, filij genht, &amp; S S. abu. troque proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentis Lomb. <hi>4.</hi> Sent. diſt. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>I baptize thee In the name of the Father that begetteth, and of the Sonne that is begotten, and of the holy Ghoſt which proceedeth from them both.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe propoſitions may have a ſpeculative truth in them, and there may be warrant for them; for it ſeemes reaſonable to think, that as (though our Saviour ſaid <hi>After this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er pray ye,</hi> Matth. 6.9 and <hi>when ye pray ſay</hi> &amp;c. Luke 11.2. yet) when we pray, it may be lawfull to uſe another forme,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:113626:33"/>or that forme with ſome expoſitory variation; ſo it may be lawfull, in reſpect of the thing it ſelfe, to uſe the ſame words, or others of the like ſenſe and meaning; and this the rather, becauſe we finde not that any other Sacrament, in the old or new Teſtament, had any ſet forme of words, wherewith it was by a preſcript order or any peremptory rule to be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred: but to be practically lawfull at this time, after ſo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and ſo generall a uſe and cuſtome of moſt orthodox Churches is another thing; For to depart from thoſe words, having ſo generall warrant, not onely from Scripture, but from univerſall obſervation, cannot be done without ſcandall, and ſo cannot be lawfully done, though the thing it ſelfe, in it ſelf and <hi>in theſi</hi> be lawfull; as though it be lawfull for a Preacher to keepe on his hat while he ſpeaketh to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and in the thing it ſelfe more congruous to his condition then to the peoples to be covered at Setmon, yet ſince it hath been ſo long a received cuſtome in our Church, for the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher not to weare his hat though the people doe, he that ſhould preach with his hat on his head, would occaſion a ſcandall, and give men occaſion to conceive. That he were ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther very proud, or very vaine and fantaſticall.</p>
               <p>The fifth Querie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If there be any variation from the forme in</hi> Matth. 28.19, <hi>what may be admitted without violation of the Sacrament, what not?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In anſwere wherto we ſay,</p>
               <p>Firſt, That ſome words in this forme are not ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and conſiderable as others, as</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is not neceſſary to ſay, <hi>I baptize thee,</hi> in the firſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; for the<note n="k" place="margin">Non nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, quia &amp; per illa verba, [Baptizetur talis ſervm Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti in nomine patris, filij, &amp; ſpir, ſaucti, vet baptizetur ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> meis ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis] verum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiatur Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſma, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Florent. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretum ſuper unione</hi> Iaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binorum <hi>&amp;</hi> Armeniorum. <hi>Franc. Long. Sum. Concil. p. 888. col. 1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Greeks,</hi> baptizing in the third perſon, <hi>Let this ſervant of Chriſt be baptized, or baptized by my hands, in the name of the Father, Sonne, and holy Gholſt,</hi> are acknowledged to have a true baptiſme.</p>
               <p>Secondly, It is not neceſſary to ſay <hi>Baptize,</hi> for a man may perform true and ſufficient baptiſme by the word <hi>waſh,</hi> or <hi>sprinkle,</hi> as well as by the word <hi>baptize.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, It makes no great difference to ſay <hi>in the name,</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:113626:34"/>or <hi>into the name,</hi> for as <hi>in the name</hi> may note the authority of Baptiſme, and the holy influence of the Authour going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with it, ſo to be baptized <hi>into Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 6.1. or <hi>into the name of Chriſt,</hi> may note the effect and benefit of Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, incorporating the baptized into the myſticall body of Jeſus Chriſt; and though we read the words, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>In the name of the Father;</hi> the Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, may more exactly in the grammaticall ſence of the words be rend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>into the name;</hi> and the like we may reſolve of the ſame phraſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.13. but to be Baptized <hi>in the name,</hi> is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the true Engliſh of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38. and of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.48. But<note n="l" place="margin">In nomine u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique art, non in nominibus, ut unitas eſſen. tiae oſtendatur, per tria verò que ſuppoſuit tres eſſe perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas declaravit. <hi>Ambroſ. de ſi de ad Gratian cap. 1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ambroſe</hi> obſerves <hi>in the Name</hi> in the ſingular number, as importing the unity of ſubſtance in the Trinity of perſons of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head.</p>
               <p>Secondly, But for the expreſſe mention of all the perſons of the Trinity, it is held by many to be<note n="m" place="margin">Aquin. <hi>in</hi> 3. <hi>part. q.</hi> 66. <hi>art.</hi> 5. <hi>ad</hi> 7. <hi>&amp; in</hi> 4 <hi>ſent. diſt</hi> 3. <hi>art.</hi> 2. <hi>queſti uncula</hi> 2. <hi>ad</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Bonarent. <hi>art. q.</hi> 3. Scotus <hi>queſt</hi> 2. <hi>art.</hi> 3 <hi>num.</hi> 16. Paludanus <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>art.</hi> 3.</note> neceſſary, both<note n="n" place="margin">Suarez. <hi>in</hi> 3. <hi>part.</hi> Thom. <hi>Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>qui eſt primus de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentis disp.</hi> 21. <hi>q.</hi> 66. <hi>Sect.</hi> 4 <hi>p.</hi> 220 <hi>col.</hi> 2.</note> becauſe of the words of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. the cuſtom of the Church, and the ſcandall which would be occaſioned if any of them ſhould be omitted. And upon this ground it is held by ſome inſufficient to baptize <hi>in the name</hi> of the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or of three perſons,<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Suar. 2.</hi> Ibid.</note> yea though in this form. <hi>I baptize thee in the name of the firſt, ſecond, and third perſon,</hi> or if there be an expreſſe mention of any two perſons, and an omiſſion of any one, it is reſolved to be no Baptiſme.<note n="p" place="margin">Sic in Epiſt. <hi>Zach.</hi> pap <hi>1.</hi> ad Boniſac. Tom. <hi>5.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil p. <hi>488.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Here may come in the Queſtion about the baptiſme of an ignorant prieſt, which was, <hi>Whether pronouncing the words of Baptiſme in</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">In nomine patria, ſtita &amp; spiritua ſancta. <hi>Aventin</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. Boior. l. <hi>3.</hi> p <hi>297.</hi> &amp; Tom <hi>5.</hi> Concil. p <hi>48.</hi> col. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>falſe Latine made a nullity of the Baptiſme? Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niface</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Mentz</hi> had commanded a child ſo bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized to be rebaptized; <hi>Virgilius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Saltsburge,</hi> and <hi>Sydonius</hi> another <hi>Bavarian</hi> Biſhop would not agree to that, for they allowed of the Baptiſme theologically, though gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matically erroncous; The reſolution referred to Pope <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> he decreed for the validity of the baptiſme, though there were ſuch an incongruity in the Prieſts pronuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, The forms of Baptiſine (ſwarivng from the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:113626:34"/>words of our. Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19.) invented and uſed by Hereticks, for intimation of ſome corrupt and hereticall doctrines; eſpecially prejudiciall to the honour of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, do make a nullity of the Baptiſme; whereof there are many ſorts.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That of<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Oſander,</hi> Centur. <hi>2.</hi> fol. <hi>42. Irenaeus</hi> ad. verſ. baereſ. l. <hi>2</hi> c. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Mark</hi> the heretick, who baptized <hi>in the name of the unknown Father of all things, into the truth the mother of all things, and in the name of the deſcondent upon Jeſu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That of the<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Athan.</hi> Serm. <hi>3.</hi> contra Aria not.</note> 
                  <hi>Arrians,</hi> who baptized <hi>in the name of the Father the onely true God, of Jeſus Christ a ereature, and of the holy Ghoſt the ſervant of them both.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it be ſaid, that the baptiſme of the <hi>Arrians</hi> was held ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient by the Catholike Church, as<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bin.</hi> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> in Can. <hi>7.</hi> Coucil. Laod. Tom. <hi>1.</hi> Concil. p. <hi>306.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Binius</hi> noteth upon the ſeventh Canon of the Councell of <hi>Laodicea</hi> and <hi>Framiſc.</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Franciſe.</hi> Long. ſumma Concil. Annet. in Concil. <hi>Laod.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> p. <hi>194.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Long</hi> his plagiary (for he ſteals his Annotations word for word, for many lines together, without a word of mention of him) It may be anſwered, that the <hi>Arrians</hi> did not all of them, or not alwaies baptize in one form, for ſometimes they baptized<note n="*" place="margin">In nom ne pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris per futum in ſpiritu ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto. <hi>Sozom. hiſtor</hi> l. <hi>6. c. 26.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>in the name of the Father, by the Son, and in the holy Ghoſt;</hi> which form (though not ſo bad as the former) was thought to be ſo diſpleaſing unto God, that he miraculouſly diſappointed the <hi>Arrian</hi> Miniſter, who meant to have Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptized one in that manner, by<note n="x" place="margin">Ibid.</note> cauſing the water ſodainly to vaniſh out of his ſight, by which the baptiſme was prevented.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That of the<note n="y" place="margin">Epiphan. ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ. <hi>76.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Eunomians,</hi> who baptized <hi>in the name of God uncreated, of the Son created, and of the holy Ghoſt the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifier, and a creature of the created Sonne;</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Theodoret.</hi> lib. <hi>4.</hi> baret. ſabt lar.</note> who out of an hereticall conceit againſt the Trinity oppoſed the mannar of trine immerſion.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That of the <hi>Photinians,</hi> whoſe form of Baptiſme (as their faith) was<note n="a" place="margin">See <hi>Bin.</hi> in Coned. Laod. Can. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Tem. 1. p. <hi>300.</hi>
                  </note> worſe then that of the <hi>Arriams;</hi> ſo much worſe that the <hi>Arians</hi> themſelves could not endure either them or it, and therefore did they excommunicare them; ſo that though ſome baptiſme of the <hi>Arrians</hi> were held ſufficient (as hath been noted) the baptiſme of the <hi>Photinians</hi> was held not onely guilty of impiety, but a meet nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:113626:35"/>
               <p n="5">5. That form of baptiſme which joyns the creature in commiſſion with the Creatour, as</p>
               <p n="1">1. That of the <hi>Pepuzians,</hi> or<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Baſil.</hi> prima jua epiſt. ad Amphiloch. I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conij Epiſc. can. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Montanists,</hi> who baptized <hi>into the Father, Sonne, and into Montunus,</hi> or <hi>Priſcilla.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That of ſome ſuperſtitious and<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gerard</hi> Loc Com. Tom. 4. col. <hi>410. § 93.</hi>
                  </note> idolatrous Papiſts, who to the Trinity of perſons added the name of <hi>Mary the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall Virgin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. That which<note n="d" place="margin">Neque enim Eccleſiaſlicam contempliſſe formam, ſed ex devotione quadam feſti. nantis fidei in banc voce eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſſe videtur. <hi>Bern.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>340. Henrico</hi> Archiacono col. <hi>1648.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bernard</hi> mentioneth of a childe whom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing newly borne, and in imminent danger of death, a lay man baptized on the ſodain, <hi>In the name of God, and of the holy and true Croſſe;</hi> which <hi>Bernard</hi> alloweth for ſufficient baptiſme, and excuſeth the man, as doing it not out of contempt of the Eccleſiaſticall forme, but of a ſodain devotion; wherein he determineth the doubt as a Papiſt, according to ſuch prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples as Proteſtants deny; and therefore they may deny that baptiſme, both in reſpect of the Agent, a meer lay-man, and in reſpect of the form, as wanting what it ſhould have, the <hi>Name of the Trinity,</hi> and having what it ſhould not, the mention of the Croſſe, a great Idoll with the Papiſts, (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially with the ignorant) though he labour to force a better ſence out of his words, then it is like the man himſelf ever meant.</p>
               <p>But what if a childe were baptized, not by a lay-man, but by a Miniſter, whether Popiſh or Evangelicall, and the words were formally uſed, which are the uſuall forme, <hi>I Baptize thee in the name of the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt,</hi> doth the addition of the Virgin <hi>Maries</hi> name make void what was done by the words precedently ſpoken? The ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition<note n="c" place="margin">Bellarm. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>de Bapt. c.</hi> 25, 26, 27.</note> of exorciſme, exſuffiation, ſalt, ſpittle, oyl, and other ceremonies doth not make a nullity of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and therefore they were not rebaptized by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants who were ſuperſtitiouſly Baptized by Popiſh prieſts.</p>
               <p>To which I anſwer, 1. That there may be more cauſe to condemne a baptiſme whoſe forme is corrupted, as that where the Virgin <hi>Maries</hi> name is added to the name of the Trinity, then where ceremonies, though ſuperfluous, and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:113626:35"/>ſuperſtitious, which Papiſts themſelves do not account of the eſſence of Baptiſme, are ſuperadded unto it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If any doubt or ſcruple yet remain, it muſt be reſolved either by comparing the danger of ſuch a corrupt baptiſme with the errour of rebaptizing in ſuch a caſe, and ſo reſolving either certainly to allow, or diſallow the Baptiſme, or elſe by making a conditionall rebaptization, as in a doubtfull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is preſcribed in the Caſhiered Servicebook, in the manner of private Baptiſme in this form, <hi>If thou be not already baptized, I baptize thee in the name of the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt;</hi> which form with water (which is the matter) are there made eſſentiall parts of Baptiſme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>Concluſion.</head>
               <p>To winde up all into a <hi>Concluſion,</hi> The diſcuſſion and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of theſe Queſtions, I have thus farre carryed on, not ſo much for confutation of M. <hi>Saltmarſh,</hi> who hath ſaid no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that might deſerve ſuch a ſcrious diſquiſition, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination, but that there might be ſomething preſented with an Anſwer to him that might be worthy of the view of an Intelligent Reader, who will hereby underſtand, that though M. <hi>Saltmarſh</hi> ſet forth ſuch trifling fancies, and worthles ſhreads, and ſnips, as are good for nothing, his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoniſt will not deal with him in trading with ſuch petty parcels, but will rather endeavour (by propoſing that to the judicious Reader that may ſome way improve his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) to make ſome amends for his extemporary em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptynes.</p>
               <p>And hereby (notwithſtanding) 1 is that novell poſiſion of his fully confuted, and his raſhnes and preſumption check<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who (having ſo little learning or reading in the ſtate and ſtory of the Churches diſpenſations through ſeverall ages of the world) in theſe dayes wherein all manner of knowledge doth ſo abound (though many of his new lights be but the flaſhes of an <hi>ignis fatuus</hi> durſt averte and publiſh in Print,<note n="e" place="margin">Smoke in the Temple, firſt Numb. and ſecond Edit. <hi>p.</hi> 13.</note> 
                  <hi>that</hi> Mat. 28.18. rather 19. Mark. 16. &amp;c. <hi>are rather and farr more probably to be expounded of the Spiries baptiſme, or of the baptiſme of the Holy ghoſt.</hi> And <hi>that the forme by which they
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:113626:36"/>baptize, viz. I baptize thee in the name of the Father, Sonne and Holy ghoſt, is a forme of mans deviſing, a tradition of man, a meer conſequence drawn from ſuppoſition and probability, and not a forme left by Chriſt to ſay over them in the water: If Chriſt had ſayd, When you baptize them ſay this over them, I baptize thee In the Name of the Father, Sonne, and Holy ghoſt, and unleſſe le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt had left this forme, thus made up to their hands, they practiſe a thing made up by themſelves, and drawn or forced out of Ieſus Chriſts words in</hi> Mat. 28.19.</p>
               <p>And if that forme were not made up by Chriſt, how will he prove that the forme of Baptiſme <hi>In the Name of the Lord Ieſus</hi> was made up by him? if not, why ſhould that be made an exception againſt baptizing <hi>In the Name of the Father, Son, and holy Ghost,</hi> and not againſt baptizing <hi>In the Name of Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. His miſſallegation of the ſaying of the learned <hi>Salmaſius</hi> is further convinced; who, becauſe he reporteth<note n="f" place="margin">Baptiſma in aquis perenne bus Apoſtolici inftituti &amp; moris, ſed non invocatio Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis ſaper baptizatum cum Apoſtoliin ſolo nomine te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu Baptiza runt. <hi>Salmaſ. in Apparatu ad lib. de pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matu papae, fol. 193.</hi>
                  </note> a matter of Apoſtolicall practice, will inferre that <hi>Salmaſius</hi> is a Dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall oppoſite to baptiſme, <hi>In the Name of the Father, Son, and boly Ghoſt.</hi> If that be his meaning to have <hi>Salmaſius</hi> ſuppoſed to hold with him in his oppoſition againſt Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing <hi>In the Name of the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt,</hi> he meaneth doubtles to put an abſurd paradox upon him, which he would ſeriouſly diſavow, if he knew it; if that be not his meaning, he citeth him to no purpoſe; and though there be ſome other learned men of <hi>Salmaſius</hi> his minde in that point, (whoſe names he citeth not, becauſe he brought in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of baptiſme not <hi>ex inſtituto,</hi> but <hi>obiter,</hi> not of purpoſe, but occaſionally) yet there are who with much confidence af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that the Apoſtles did baptize <hi>In the name of the Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt,</hi> and not <hi>In the Name of Jeſus</hi> onely, as hath been before declared; and the reaſon is, becauſe though there be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o clear proof of their practiſe of either in the Scripture, yet the words of our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. are more expreſſe and plain for baptizing <hi>In the Name of the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt,</hi> then any text is for a rule of any other forme.</p>
               <p>For his <hi>testimony</hi> produced and pretended to be in favour
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:113626:36"/>of Independency of Churches, I will deſire to trouble the Reader no further, but to review what M. <hi>L.</hi> hath<note n="g" place="margin">In his book of <hi>Light for ſmoke a p.</hi> 53. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ad</hi> 97.</note> written in anſwer to it already, and oy that he will ſee that M. <hi>Saltm.</hi> in this controverſy is deſtitute both of a good cauſe and of a good conſcience; of a <hi>good cauſe,</hi> for his eppealing to <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſius</hi> as to a patrone of Independency is at leaſt a belying of him; and of a <hi>good couſciouce,</hi> becauſe that being diſcovered, he ſtill oppoſeth and outfaceth it as much as he can, againſt an evident conviction.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="animadversion">
            <head>A brief <hi>Animadverſion</hi> upon the mad Pamphle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, compoſer of the <hi>Perſume</hi> &amp;c. who out of two letters C. D. by a rare ſpel of Daemonology hath rayſed <hi>Cerberus Diabolus,</hi> yet withall, to give the devil his due, A word of <hi>Apology</hi> for him againſt the poſted reproach put upon him by <hi>Iohn Saltmarſh,</hi> and <hi>Giles Calvert.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe unſavoury Pamphlet called a <hi>Perſume</hi> came out with ſuch a ſtinck, that thoſe that had not loſt their ſence of ſmelling cryed <hi>Fye upon is,</hi> &amp; ſtopped their noſes at it; and if it had been written againſt me I would have thought it worthy of none other Anſwer, then ſuch as I finde in <hi>Elian</hi> which the <hi>Ephori</hi> of <hi>Lacedaemon</hi> made to the <hi>Clazomenians,</hi> when with ſoot they had ſoyled their ſeats of Iudgment; which was that they cauſed to be proclaimed throughout the City, that,<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elian, var. hiſt. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>15</hi> p. <hi>5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>it ſhould be lawfull for the</hi> Clazomenians <hi>to doe undecent things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet though neither I non C. D. (who hath ſo foundly ſcourged him that it could not be but he muſt ſnarle and howle like a dog under the whippe) meddle with him any
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:113626:37"/>more, he cannot paſſe without a laſt from the hand of a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate adverſary, the <hi>Moderate Intelligencer,</hi> who (though they be both of one trade (viz. Newſmongers) is in his weekly Intelligence as farr above this <hi>Perfumer,</hi> the ſcribler, of miſcalled <hi>Perfect Paſſages</hi> and <hi>Perfect Occurrences,</hi> as the moſt artificiall tayler is above the moſt bungling botchet in the City. And he hath ſhaped him a Cenſure in theſe termes,<note n="i" place="margin">Moderat. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell. <hi>Numb.</hi> 59. <hi>p.</hi> 405.</note> 
               <hi>A pamphlet came out on</hi> Monday <hi>laſt called</hi> A perfume againſt the ſulpherous &amp;c. <hi>ſayd in the title to be written by</hi> Iohn Salt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marſh, <hi>is put out wrongfully in his name, and is none of his. Shall we never be ridd of theſe Mountebanks and Impoſters? who when they have not braynes to publiſh any thing of worth, feign frothy titles, when no ſuch thing is in the Book; but to put the name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayd to ſo ridiculous a peice as this, argues the Author to have needed long ſince to be cut of the ſimples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For feare leſt this<note n="k" place="margin">Brevibus Gy aris &amp; carce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re dignus.</note> worthy writer M. <hi>Iohn Saltmarſh</hi> ſhould receive reproach by ſuch a ſenſeleſſe pamphlet, or <hi>Giles Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert</hi> his Stationer ſuſtain loſſe by diſreputation of his papers in time to come, this Antidote was poſted up in ſeverall places for publike view, <hi>A pamphlet came out on Monday,</hi> April. 19. 1646. <hi>called</hi> A perſume againſt the ſulpherous &amp;c. <hi>ſayd in the title to be written by</hi> Iohn Saltmarſh, <hi>is put out wrongfully in his name, and is none of his.</hi> Giles Calvert.</p>
            <p>Which is enough for a ſuperſedeas to any ingenuous man for any further Reply unto it, for ſuch a one may very wel diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain to anſwer that which ſuch an Author diſdaynes to own. Yet, to ſay the truth, both M. <hi>Saltmarſh,</hi> and M. <hi>Calvert</hi> did the fellow wrong; and becauſe I ſee he is ſo ſilly that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell how to make his own defence himſelf, I will helpe him out.</p>
            <p>He ſayth for himſelf, that M. <hi>Saltmarſh can blears him shat he writ his name and Title,</hi> and <hi>with that it was licenſed;</hi> and <hi>that the Printer acknowledged his fault.</hi> The more unwiſe man he, and no wiſer are they (M. <hi>Saltmarſh</hi> and M. <hi>Calvert</hi> not excepted) who ſo groſſely miſtook the title page of the Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet; which makes not M. <hi>Saltmarſh</hi> the Author of the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume,</hi> for his name is not brought in till the letter end of the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:113626:37"/>page, preſently upon <hi>the Smoke in the Temp.</hi> which was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and Printed with the name of <hi>John Saltmarſh,</hi> and is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged both by himſelf and his Stationer to be his. So, you ſee here is need of more <hi>Light</hi> to diſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll the darknes of this <hi>Perfume</hi> now, as well as of his <hi>Spoke</hi> before.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
